<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to certain seditious and Jesuitical queres heretofore purposely and maliciously cast out to retard and hinder the English forces in their going over into Ireland ...</title>
            <author>Waring, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13315015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13315015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99021</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99021)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 442:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to certain seditious and Jesuitical queres heretofore purposely and maliciously cast out to retard and hinder the English forces in their going over into Ireland ...</title>
                  <author>Waring, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du-Gard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedicatory signed: Tho. Waring.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Irish question.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To certain ſeditious and Jeſuitical Queres, Heretofore purpoſely and maliciouſly caſt out, to retard and hinder the <hi>Engliſh</hi> forces in their going over into <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby is fully proved that the <hi>Britiſh</hi> were the firſt, and moſt ancient Proprietors and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that Land (which was at the firſt called <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Leſs</hi>) before the acceſſion of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> thither, and that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> came in but by the ſufferance of the <hi>Britiſh;</hi> Of what Countrie the <hi>Iriſh</hi> at the firſt were; their often rebellions and defections; the ſubduing and reducing all of them to obedience, aſwel long before the Conqueſt of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Norman,</hi> as ſince; together alſo with the names of the new Kings, which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have lately elected and made amongſt themſelvs, with manie other neceſſarie diſcoveries of great concernment, fully manifeſting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt to that Land, and the miſerable ſufferings of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, in all ages, by the barbarous and bloudie actions of the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by WILLIAM Du-GARD, Printer</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable The Lord PRESIDENT, and COUNCIL of STATE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's not my abilitie, but the force of the Cauſ, and neceſsitie of this task (others of better parts beeing ſilent) that prompt mee to challenge an intereſt in your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor's patronage of my weak endeavors in aſſerting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt a more dangerous then known ſtickler for the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and their gangren'd Cauſ, diſcovering himſelf in ſom pernicious <hi>Queres,</hi> cunningly diſperſed at ſuch a ſeaſon, wherein they might have a full influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the common genius of the Armie, then deſigned for <hi>Ireland:</hi> And finding light ſufficient in my ſelf from ſuch experimental truths, as lodg in my own boſom, to diſcover the <hi>Queriſt's Preſtigies;</hi> I have adventured a little to draw the curtain, and make way for ſom more fit and able, to vindicate the just intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> against their cauſleſs and implacable enemies, the barbarous <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels. This piece beeing onely intended as an incitement thereunto. And ſuch it will ſurely prove, if it finde your honor's fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable aſpect, and the like approbation from thoſe other wiſe ſteers-men, whom the Lord hath placed at the helm of
<pb facs="tcp:99021:3"/>this Nation's Government: And for thoſe adherents to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whoſe mindes are fore-stalled, and carried away with the ſtream of their falſ aſſeverations, and loſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of their modestie in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> impudencie, (although I wiſh they may bee in their Judgments rectified, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners reformed,) yet I value not their carpings nor vain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; <hi>Quia Momus nunquam gnarus eſt.</hi> I onely beg your honor's acceptance of theſe lines from my poor hand, ſo as my joies may bee continued in the memorie of your good Acts; my affection owe's a dutie to the performance of this work, which will at laſt toll in better Ringers, proſtrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my endeavors at the feet of your honors, as thoſe of a ſublime underſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Your Honor's moſt humble and engaged Servant THO. WARING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:3"/>
            <head>TO HIS EXCELLENCIE Oliver Cromwel, Lord GENERAL of the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">And alſo to the Right Honorable <hi>HENRIE IRETON,</hi> Lord Deputie of IRELAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He preſent ſeed of the ancient <hi>Scythians,</hi> and other barbarous Eaſterlings (the now <hi>Iriſh,</hi> aſſiſted with ſom collapſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and degenerate <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts, ſtriking at the verie root of the tree of <hi>Proteſtaniſm,</hi> do not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs with their barbarous torturing, and murdering of vaſt numbers of our Religion, and blood, everie daies fierie malice (as I may ſaie) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a new waie of the moſt exſecrable and amaru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tortures of thoſe moſt innocent people in cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of blood, wherein they glutted themſelvs. But of late, finding the ſword of God drawn out, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by your Excellencie, and ſeeing the noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpirits impatient, until God by his and their ſwords ſhould avenge their brethren's bloods by the deſtruction of that inhumane generation; Som of them, as far as poſſible, to take off the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute intentions of the Proteſtant ſouldierie from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliating upon the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſuch deſtruction, as they had
<pb facs="tcp:99021:4"/>generally vowed to exerciſe upon us all, have caſt out certain cavelling and ſeditious <hi>Queres;</hi> whereby they would amaze and blinde ſom inadvertent men, excuſe or at leaſt extenuate their own high offences, make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt to <hi>Ireland</hi> ſeem dubious, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to bee the ancient proprietors of that Land, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo, with a ſublime diſdain, inveighing againſt Conquerors and Conqueſts, (the greateſt perſons and moſt common intereſts of all the whole world) which is a boldneſs without paralel.</p>
            <p>Now, others of better talent, and more verſed in the antiquities of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſparing their pens, I have taken up the boldneſs (out of ſmall abilitie) to contrive the following Anſwers to thoſe <hi>Queres,</hi> by which, if anie (formerly ſeduced by the vain pretences of the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) bee untwined from them, and brought within the ſight of the truth, I have my deſires. And as your excellencie's valor againſt theſe Monſters of men, hath by God's aſſiſtance quelled their furies, and your wiſdom infatuated their Counſels: ſo I doubt not, but the eie of your Judgment hath diſcerned their blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſubtil intentions, in part declared by their actions: I am yet a ſtranger to your Excellencie's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but not to your heroïck, noble and pious deeds: My lines (though not ſatisfactorie) I beſeech you yet take in ſuch worth, as when peruſed, you will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to call upon more able pens to perform that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wherein (unwillingly) I am yet deficient; the great God of truth ſo order all your Councils, and Actions, that they maybee crowned with a glorious and your moſt deſired ſucceſs, ſo praye's</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellencie's moſt humble Servant <hi>THO. WARING.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:99021:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here hath bin lately publiſhed a certain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Pamphlet, intituled <hi>Queres,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the conſideration of ſuch as were intended for the ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which as it ſeem's was brought in by one <hi>Gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> (of an Iriſh name) and one, who as (I have been informed ſince) is a Jeſuit of that Countrie: This man in formalitie, ſmoothly preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to righteouſnes, but in realitie (diſcernable to the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt apprehenſion) hatcheth and harboureth horrible, helliſh and moſt bloudie thoughts; and inflamed with a fierie malice, thirſteth after the destruction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, the exſtirpation of all the Religious Engliſh in that Land, both root and branch, together with their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest there, and would by his ſubtil and numerous queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſhearten the conſcientious noble Engliſh Spirits, from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging that way either in perſon or expence, to reduce that Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from meer barbariſm and Idolatrie, to the true worſhip of God, and obedience to the Laws, eſtabliſhed by the antient proprietors of that Nation (the Engliſh) and both antiently
<pb facs="tcp:99021:5"/>and lately ſubmitted unto by all Inhabitants of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But if you mark this Queriſt, hee perſueth the ſophiſtrie and ſubtiltie, antiently practiſed by the Jeſuits; &amp; ſo farr as hee would have all his Queſtions believed and grounded upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truths, and to bee admitted as verities: And although theſe Queres (being ſo uncertainely and falſly grounded) are worthie of no anſwer at all, having all along the plain marks of inſoliditie and ſedition upon them: yet to ſatisfie the doubts of ſuch judicious and upright men, as onely deſire to know the truth, and com not with a minde pre-occupate, and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by injurious principles.</p>
            <p>I ſhall indeavor to lay open the Queriſt's errors and delire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, reſolve the <hi>Queres</hi> hee makes, and diſcover the truth in the things hee moſt harp's upon, for his advantage; and becauſ I conceiv the Jeſuit's firſt <hi>Quere</hi> (though not in plain words) yet implicitely, by inſinuation, intend's principally <hi>Ireland and the pretended intereſt of the Iriſh</hi> (as hee in ſom of them after expreſſeth) And although alſo my ſhort and weak wings are farr deficient to ſoar ſo high a pitch, as to cite all, or neer the ſum of all authentick Authors and Records, manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the proprietie, right, and intereſt of the Land of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be originally in the Britiſh, yet becauſ thoſe of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>England</hi> (already led away with the aërie, and vain pretenſes of the Iriſh, and who never yet ſcrutinized the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh intereſt) may bee undeceived, made ſenſible of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer errors, poſſeſſed with the Engliſh right, bee acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the iterated rebellions of the Iriſh in manie ages, the often reducing, and bringing them to ſubjection, by the Britiſh or Engliſh, and with other things by theſe <hi>Queres</hi> made diſputable, I ſhall freely contribute my Talent to this ſo neceſſarie work, and firſt ſet down the <hi>Queres</hi> in order, and then anſwer them ſeverally.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99021:5"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE Irish Queres.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The firſt Quere.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the Land or inheritance that a Nation hath for ſom hundreds or thouſands of yeers enjoyed, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed without any others laying claim to have a more ſpecial right to the ſame, bee not their ſpecial right which God and nature hath given them?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The firſt Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IN this firſt Quere, the Queriſt deſire's to have it inferred, and alſo granted, that the Iriſh Inhabitants, as they now ſtand in oppoſition to <hi>England,</hi> are an entire Nation, and that they were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99021:6"/>the firſt and ſole Proprietors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as given unto them by God and nature, whereas in truth they are a people compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed partly of the old <hi>Britains,</hi> the firſt Inhabitants thereof, partly of <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Gothes,</hi> ſent thither out of <hi>Biſcaie</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> partly of <hi>Danes</hi> and other <hi>Eaſterlings,</hi> ſom ſent in by the Kings of <hi>Britain,</hi> and others intruding themſelvs, and principallly of Engliſh ſent thither, by the Kings of <hi>England</hi> in ſeveral ages, as in the enſuing diſcourſ ſhall appear, ſo as the fraud and fallacie of this firſt Quere being cleerly laid open, ſtrike's farr to the anſwering of all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>And firſt to ſay ſomthing of the ſoil and Iſland, now called <hi>Ireland,</hi> which by ſeveral ancient writers hath been rendred by ſeveral other names, ſignifying (for the moſt part) that it is a Weſtern part of <hi>Britain,</hi> which the very name now given unto it by the Iriſh, <hi>viz. Eirin,</hi> ſignifying a weſtern Countrie, doth much demonſtrate, and beſides, at this day a part of <hi>Mounſter</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> is called <hi>Hiermoun,</hi> in Engliſh, <hi>Weſt-Mounſter,</hi> which ſhew the name <hi>Eirin</hi> to bee derived from <hi>Hier,</hi> which is weſt, as appear's plainly by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Cambden</hi> (a faithful relater of the beſt antiquities extant:) the ancient Geographer writeth in theſe words, of Iſlands for greatneſs, the <hi>Indian Taprobane</hi> is prime and principal, next after it, <hi>Britain,</hi> and in third de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, another <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſland called <hi>Hibernia,</hi> (that is <hi>Ireland</hi>) whereupon <hi>Ptolomie</hi> in his writings of Geographie, call's it in plain words <hi>Britannia parva,</hi> the old Geographers called it the <hi>Britains</hi> Iſland; <hi>Strabo</hi> called the Inhabitants <hi>Britains. Diodorus Siculus</hi> termed <hi>Irin</hi> a part of Britain, and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his book <hi>de mundo,</hi> Cap. 3. hath theſe words as they ſtand tranſlated, <hi>viz. Ibi ſunt Inſulae, quae quantitate maximae habentur, numero verò duae ſunt, Britanicae dicuntur, Albion &amp; Hibernia.</hi> By all which it fall's cleer that by the moſt ancient and authentick writers, the Iſland of <hi>Ireland</hi> was ever taken and accounted a Britiſh Iſland, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to great Britain, neither is it found in any approved Writer or Record, that ever any King or Potentate claimed right or intereſt in the ſoil or Land of that Iſland, ſave only the Kings of great Britain, in right of their Kingdom, now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>England,</hi> which in ſeveral ages they have not failed to doe, by reducing and ſubduing the unjuſt rebellion, and uſurpation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99021:6"/>of thoſe unrulie Inhabitants, and if you look into Monuments or Records of later time, you ſhall never finde it called a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or a Realm, till in the reign of <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. when by Act of Parlament, it was made and ſtyled a Kingdom, and that King declared, and confeſſed King thereof, unanimouſly agreed by all the Inhabitants of that Iſland. But that by all Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament in that Land, and other Records, it was alwaies till then, for 400 yeers or thereabouts called the King's land <hi>of Ireland,</hi> and by ſeveral Acts of Parlament, <hi>viz.</hi> one Act in the twentie eighth yeer of that King, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8 reign Cap. 2. That Land is declared to be appending and belonging to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And by another Act there made in that King's reign, the ſaid Iſland is declared to be a Member, appending and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully belonging to <hi>England,</hi> and united to the ſame; and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other Acts there the ſame in ſubſtance is aſſerted, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and all this agreed and aſſented unto by the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors of thoſe now in Arms there againſt <hi>England,</hi> and the Governors thereof; and yet by this Queriſt it is eſteemed to bee an Original, entire Nation, diſtinct from any Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, yea ſuch, as hee ſcruple's to have them call'd Rebels.</p>
                  <p>Thus having given you the opinion and report of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and ſom modern proofs of the denomination, and full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that Iſland to Great <hi>Britain,</hi> it will bee requiſite, that by the like ancient and modern evidence the juſt right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of the Engliſh to that Land, and to the dominion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to the naturall ſubjection of all the Inhabitants thereof to <hi>England,</hi> bee alſo manifeſted and avowed, the better to let the world ſee the Queriſt's fraud, and ſubtiltie in this general vaſt Quere, and indeed throughout all the reſt of his abuſive Queres and inſinuations.</p>
                  <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Cambden,</hi> that faithfull ſearcher into Antiquities, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that moſt of the beſt approved and knowing Writers out of Antiquities, do determin that the firſt known Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> were <hi>Britains</hi> ſent thither, by the Kings of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> of which opinion he conclude's himſelf to bee, but that they could not ſend ſufficient Inhabitants, to repleniſh ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and that by a great mortalitie happening among them, they were much diminiſhed; and you may perceiv by a Statute
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99021:7"/>made in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the 11. yeer of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> (by ſom Writers called <hi>Gorgund</hi>) Son to <hi>Belin</hi> King of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> was Lord of <hi>Biſcaie</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> (as his poſteritie long after him continued) and having occaſion to com into <hi>Britain,</hi> his Father being dead he voyaged into <hi>Denmak,</hi> and in his return a great multitude of his Subjects of <hi>Biſcaie</hi> met him at Sea, (being ſtreightned for relief in their Countrie) and humbly beſought him to aſſign them ſom place for habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, whereunto (by advice of his Council, he aſſented, and directed them to his Iſland, now called <hi>Ireland,</hi> which wanted people, and ſent with them guides, to bring them thither, where finding a fertile ſoil, they encreaſed abundantly, bringing their language with them, and being then the greater number of people, after the new acceſs, involved the <hi>Britiſh</hi>-tongue into theirs, (yet in ſom ſort mixed) as may appear by many new words and names of things, well underſtood by the <hi>Welſh.</hi> It being of dailie experience, that the <hi>Welſh</hi> do much more ſoon and eaſilie learn <hi>Iriſh</hi> then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> can do, and that much of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> is underſtood by them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Giraldus Cambrenſis</hi> called theſe <hi>Biſcayners, Beſclenſes,</hi> and <hi>Cambden</hi> write's very largely of their Anceſtors coming into <hi>Spain,</hi> at the confluence of the Northern Nations into thoſe parts, alleging that part of them were <hi>Scythians,</hi> and part <hi>Gothes,</hi> and to add to the truth of this relation, their ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither is ſpecified in many of the rude, (yet ancient) <hi>Iriſh</hi> annals, both in Iriſh and Latine.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Britiſh</hi> Hiſtories, and ſom of the Engliſh Chronicles do make mention of <hi>Hiberus</hi> and <hi>Hermion,</hi> then Captains of thoſe <hi>Beſclenſes,</hi> and their <hi>Bards</hi> (who to this daie keep, and at all feaſts and publique meetings, do chaunt and publiſh the Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digrees and Acts of the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) do derive the moſt ancient <hi>Iriſh</hi> from thoſe that came out of <hi>Spain,</hi> rather chooſing to glorifie themſelvs in them, then from the <hi>Britains,</hi> from whom ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them are deſcended, and from whom they had permiſſion to dwell there: For, doubtleſs, there are manie evident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, that much of the Eaſt part of that Iſland, continued ſtill inhabited by <hi>Britains,</hi> and that thoſe <hi>Beſclenſes,</hi> moſt inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the more Weſtern parts of <hi>Mounſter,</hi> and <hi>Connaght,</hi> where
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99021:7"/>their former neighbors and friends might moſt eaſily eom to them, yet diſperſed as they found cauſ; thoſe in the Weſtern parts ſpeaking more broad, do hardly underſtand much of the language of the other: And to ſhew further, that the Britains had a good ſhare in the Original anceſtrie of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the verie Officers which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have from age to age uſed for their pedigrees, and Annals are to this daie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Bards, which were the ſame in office and denomination, imploied by the ancient Britains; And for their manner of holding Land, it was till the firſt year of King <hi>James,</hi> by <hi>Gavelkind,</hi> as the ancient Britains held theirs, though ſo corrupted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as when the Laws came to bee ſetled in the begining of King <hi>James</hi> his time, it was adjudged a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and unreaſonable cuſtom, and ſo aboliſhed; Alſo their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cuſtom of <hi>Taineſtrie,</hi> which they called their Law, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from Britiſh, for, amongſt them the word <hi>Tane,</hi> or <hi>Thane</hi> ſignified an Elder, Governor, or Lord of a territorie; And the ſame word amongſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had the ſame ſence, and therefore the ſecond perſon to the Lord of the Countrie, who was to ſucceed (if a ſtronger force interpos'd not) was called the <hi>Tanaiſt</hi> ſetled upon him, as <hi>Seniori &amp; digniori,</hi> and hee had Lands and Impoſitions on the Countrie aſſigned to him in right of that Office; The Lord alſo of the Countrie beeing put into Office by the ſame Law (where force did not overbear it) all which, is now alſo aboliſhed as unlawful. It appear's alſo by antiquitie, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> agreed with the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in the cuſtom of obſerving the time of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> both then, therein differing from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt known Inhabitants beeing thus ſent into, and ſetled in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Britains, they ſo continued in ſubjection to the King of great Britain for ſeveral ages, the contrarie whereof hath appeared in no memorie; And to enter into further Inquiſition thereinto is not much material, no other King, Prince or Potentate, having at anie time made claim unto them, until the Romans entered Britain, and held the ſame by conqueſt, after manie and often conflicts; In all which time, during their ſtrugling againſt, and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Romans, the Britiſh could not have that care
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99021:8"/>and over-ſight of them, as formerly they had, ſo as in that time they took head, and ſet up amongſt them, in a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous waie, Rulers and pettie Kings; which Rulers and Kings <hi>Giraldus Cambrenſis</hi> calleth Tributaries, and what kinde of Kings thoſe then were, and afterwards continued to bee, till King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond's entrie into <hi>Ireland,</hi> may much appear in an ancient Manuſcript, called the Book of Chriſt-Church in <hi>Dublin,</hi> (then a priorie) lately a Cathedral Church; In which Manuſcript are theſe words concerning them, <hi>viz. Iſti Reges non fuerunt ordinati ſolemnitate alicujus ordinis nec uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Sacramento, nec jure hereditario, vel aliquâ proprietatis ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, ſed vi &amp; armis quilibet regnum ſuum obtinuit:</hi> In all which time of the Roman's power in great Britain, neither the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Britains in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor thoſe permitted new-com <hi>Beſclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> could extinguiſh or alter the original right, which the Kings of great Britain undeniably had to their dominion there, or to thoſe Inhabitant's ſubjection.</p>
                  <p>It appeareth in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Cambden's</hi> and other Chronicles, and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, that during the Roman's power in great Britain, the Norweyans and other Eaſterlings, by waie of piracie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſion infeſted thoſe inhabitants of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and though often beaten off, yet manie got footing there, the Monuments of whom remain to this daie; and in after times when the <hi>Saxons</hi> warred in Britain, they ſeveral times came over again, and ſo ſetled on manie of the Sea-coaſts, as they built of the walled Sea-Towns, excluding from amongſt them the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them entrance, other then with great caution for Merchandiſe onely; And whereas the <hi>Queriſt</hi> would have it believed, that the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as an entire Nation, were originally impropriated in <hi>Ireland</hi> by God and nature, for manie hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, and ſome thouſands of years, without anie others laying claim to have ſpecial right to the ſame, which (hee ſeem's to inſinuate) did ſo continue to theſe times; It doth and will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear aſwel by what is formerly here remembred, as what ſhall follow in this enſuing tract, that it is a ridiculous and illuſive ſurmiſe; for it muſt not bee forgotten (eſpecially appearing by good Hiſtorie, that ſoon after the Roman's departure out of great Britain, the noble Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> obteined that Land,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99021:8"/>who beeing a man of great action, aſwel at home as abroad, paſſed into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and reduced thoſe Inhabitants to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Subjection; In proof whereof, having ſom years after occaſion for a time to keep his Court at <hi>Carlion,</hi> in great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, hee ſummoned the Governors, and pettie Kings of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (of whom one, <hi>viz.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Gellomurroe,</hi> or Mr <hi>Gillemurry</hi> is by name recorded, to appear before him at <hi>Carlion</hi> aforeſaid) there to do their homage to him; who thereupon came and performed the ſame accordingly, which was don in the year after our Saviour's nativitie, 579; and this prove's a claim at leaſt, made by the Kings of great Britain to the Iſland of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as part of their dominions; Afterwards, as is known to all men of anie reading, the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Angles</hi> out of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie</hi> invaded great Britain, and by manie conteſts in Arms, and bloudie Battels obteined the Dominion thereof, dividing it into ſeveral Kingdoms amongſt themſelvs, which continued for manie years; In all which times the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Inhabitants took more Libertie to root themſelvs in their barbarous uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and tyrannie: for wee cannot finde, that then, before, or ſince they eſtabliſhed anie certain Government, either regal or otherwiſe, neither are there extant anie authentick me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, of anie certain or paſſable Laws ordeined by them, for the regulating of anie Chriſtian people; yet ſoon after, the <hi>Saxon's</hi> Heptarchie was reduced into an Entire Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie; It is manifeſt by good Hiſtorie and Record, that <hi>Edgar</hi> King of great Britain (then and now called <hi>England</hi>) not unmindful of that Kingdom's ancient right and intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> labored, and obteined another reducement, and had the poſſeſſion of moſt of that continent, as appear's by the Books of that excellent writer Judg <hi>Cook,</hi> extracted out of Records of the Tower; Afterwards, when the <hi>Danes</hi> obtein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Rule and power in great Britain, they ſo little forgot the ancient and juſt challenge to <hi>Ireland,</hi> as that they ſent thither good numbers of men who gained large footing in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of the beſt parts of the Iſland, of whom there yet remain manie viſible Monuments, as their intrenchments, and Fortifications to this daie, called <hi>Danes</hi> Mounts, or Rathes, in <hi>Iriſh</hi> Liſſes, and round ſlender high Towers, yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99021:9"/>called <hi>Danes</hi> Steeples, or <hi>Danes</hi> Towers, yea, the beſt and largeſt Suburbs about <hi>Dublin</hi> is yet called <hi>Oſtmantown,</hi> which term the <hi>Saxons</hi> gave to the <hi>Danes</hi> as Eaſterlings, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it is their then acceſs, and ſom former incurſions made by them as aforeſaid, which left manie of them there fixed, who were the anceſtors to the now pretended original Nation, as pretended to bee given to them by God and Nature; After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the Norman <hi>William,</hi> the Conqueror, became poſſeſſed of the Dominions of <hi>England,</hi> it is univerſally known what buſineſs hee had, aſwel to ſettle that ſo gained Land, as to content his Allies, and parties brought with him, and to preſerv what hee left behind him in <hi>France,</hi> to which retroſpect hee was enforced by manie diſturbances and attempts; neither is it unknown, how unwarrantably his three next ſucceſſors came to the Crown in <hi>England,</hi> and againſt what counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workings, and heart-burnings, they held Regencie there, beſides their diſtractions in their affairs, and from their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of <hi>France,</hi> beeing not free from incumbrances of <hi>Scots,</hi> and <hi>Welſh,</hi> whereby all judicious men may conclude, that none of them could ſafely embrace the reſtitution of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> howſoever it concerned them. But aſſoon as one lineal deſcent had ſetled the Crown of <hi>England</hi> upon King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, who was great Granchilde of the ſaid <hi>William,</hi> the Norman; and who is recorded to bee the moſt powerful <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Monarch, both in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> ſince the <hi>Normans</hi> coming in; That King applied to the Pope for his conſent, to regain his ſaid Land of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who conſenting thereunto, to the end it might bee brought into orderly Government, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil, Hee yet ſuſpended all action thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſom years, beeing interrupted by his affairs in <hi>France,</hi> and the diſobedient combinations of his ſons; But after, an occaſion hapning by the invocation of one of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> pettie Kings, hee permitted manie of his Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> to paſs thither, who by their valor, poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs of a good part of that Iſland; Then in the year 1172 did that King with a competent Armie repair thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in perſon, and reſumed into his hands his ancient right of Dominion and intereſt there, without much bloudſhed, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99021:9"/>was therein confirmed by the abſolute and free ſubmiſſions of all the pettie Kings, and other Rulers, aſwel Eccleſiaſtical as Temporal, and by all others then of anie value there, which they delivered unto him under their Seals; There did hee alſo receiv the Homage, Fealtie, Allegiance, and ſubjection of all thoſe pettie uſurping Princes, and others as his Liege Subjects; There did hee hold a great Council, or general Aſſmblie of all the Prime inhabitants of that Iſland, at <hi>Liſmore,</hi> which they called a Parlament, and gave them the Engliſh Laws. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Leges Angliae ab omnibus ſunt gratanter receptae &amp; juratoriâ cautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one praeſtitâ, confirmatae.</hi> There did hee ſend his Mandats to the Archbiſhops, Biſhops and Clergie of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to aſſemble in a Synod at <hi>Caſhel,</hi> wherein <hi>Cbriſtianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Liſmore</hi> was Preſident, in which Synod that King's entrance, actions and atchievments there were declared to bee lawful; and it was there alſo concluded, that it was moſt meet, that as <hi>Ireland</hi> by God's appointment had recovered a lawful Lord and King from <hi>England;</hi> ſo alſo they ſhould from thence receiv a better from of living; they alſo then eſtabliſhed that all Divine Offices of holy Church, ſhould from thenceforth bee handled in all parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> according as the Church of <hi>England</hi> did obſerv them: In that Synod alſo, they made divers other Canons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church-Government there, which Acts were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the Regal Autoritie of the ſame <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond: To the ſame purpoſes, another general Synod was ſoon after held at <hi>Armagh</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> where the ſame things, and others for right ordering of that Government were reſolved and agreed upon: There was alſo placed <hi>Hugh Lacie</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the Government of that Land, wherein that Land then ſeemed to bee formally ſetled in a peaceable ſubject con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to <hi>England,</hi> as it ought to bee. Thus may the <hi>Queriſt,</hi> and all others ſee that that Land, and ſuppoſed original Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did not continue manie hundreds or thouſands of years, nor was enjoied till theſe times, without anie others laying claim to have right to the ſame. It may bee demanded (though ſtanding thus) how might King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond ſeiz all that Land into his own hands, and grant it to adventurers (as after hee did) To this the anſwer is eaſie; For, in a ſhort
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99021:10"/>time after, that King and the greateſt part of his Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew into <hi>England;</hi> Then did all thoſe pettie Kings, Rulers, and men of value, and the other Inhabitants falſly and traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly join in a Confederacie and action to extirpate, and expulſ all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Welſh,</hi> then left there, and did caſt aſide their dutie and obedience to <hi>England,</hi> and the good order and Laws, ſo freely and lately entertained by them, breaking all Faith and Allegiance to him, to whom they had formerly ſworn it; they murthered as manie as they could take at advantage, and at laſt beſieged <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other Towns, intending to deſtroie all the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> But the valor of thoſe men left there, and the vigilance of that King to reliev them did ſtoutly beat them off, and fruſtrated their unchriſtian intention. Then that King finding them ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked in their former rudeneſs, and barbariſme, as there was no faith or dutie to bee exſpected from them, and that they could not ſit down in anie civil ſocietie, Hee, by advice of his Council confiſcated all their Eſtates, and adjudged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the <hi>Iriſh</hi> generally to bee enemies and aliens, (in which condition they continued long after) as is manifeſt by the Records, and Statute-Laws of thoſe times,) And then hee ſet his Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> at full Libertie, to win what they could in that Land, towards the reducement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to his juſt Subjection: for better accompliſhment whereof, hee made choiſ of ten ſpecial perſons of qualitie and power in his other Dominions, to whom, by grant of inheritance, hee divided the Lands of that whole Iſland, who drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether their ſeveral Alies, friends, and other adventurers; they by that King's countenance and aſſiſtance ſo beſtirred themſelvs, as within few years they became Maſters, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of the whole Iſland, and ſo continued quietly, poſſeſſed for almoſt one hundred years, without anie offence to <hi>England,</hi> forcing the perfidious <hi>Iriſh</hi> (who were then few in number, after manie conflicts with them) into Mountains, Bogs, and boggie woods, there to wander up and down, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main of their Cattel, not daring to bee ſeen, or to graze in anie of the more habitable parts, where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſpecial Statute-Laws prohibiting the ſame; Laws alſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99021:10"/>were made, that upon pain of fellonie, no Merchant, or, other liege perſon ſhould trade with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in market, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; It was alſo made fellonie to ſuccor anie of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; from the time of the foreſaid diviſion forward, was that Iſland onely called the King's Land of <hi>Ireland,</hi> till the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth, as appear's by Acts of Parlament, and all Records mentioning the ſame; The diviſion hee made was as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> of <hi>Strigil,</hi> called <hi>Strongbow,</hi> he regranted the Kingdom, or Territories of <hi>Leimſter</hi> (ſurrendred to him by the ſaid Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> whoſe it was pretended to bee, in right of his wife, ſole daughter and heir of the laſt nominal, or tributarie King thereof, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſom lands thereunto lying, part whereof is yet called the King's Land; and beeing divided into Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, the Free-holders paie chief rents into the Exchequer to this daie, and except ſom maritim Towns, Caſtles, and ſom lands about them which hee reſerved to himſelf; To <hi>Bobert Fitz-Stephens</hi> and <hi>Myles Cogan,</hi> hee granted the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories called the Kingdom of <hi>Cork,</hi> the Citie of <hi>Cork,</hi> and ſom lands thereunto lying reſerved, as aforeſaid excepted (the heir of <hi>Cogan</hi> is yet poſſeſſor of ſom of thoſe lands) To <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip le Bruce,</hi> the Territories called the Kingdom of <hi>Limerick,</hi> with donation of Biſhopricks, and Abbeies, except the Citie of <hi>Limerick,</hi> and a Cantred of Land adjoining, reſerved as aforeſaid; To S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hugh de Lacie</hi> Juſtice, or (as ſom write) <hi>Cuſtos</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the territories called the Kingdom of <hi>Meath,</hi> then of far greater extent, then the name <hi>Meath</hi> now import's; To S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>John de Courſie</hi> all <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> which beeing a large continent, was quietly poſſeſſed by him, and his <hi>Engliſh</hi> tenements ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie years; After his death (without heirs) it was granted to <hi>Hugh Lacie,</hi> who held it, till forfeited; then was it granted by King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, to <hi>Walter de Burgo</hi> from whom it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to <hi>William de Burgo;</hi> And after thoſe Lands and Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories were by <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth adjoined to the <hi>Demeſne,</hi> and Crown-Lands of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To <hi>William Fitz-Adelme de Burgo</hi> all <hi>Connaght,</hi> except a ſmall part for life given to <hi>Rotherick,</hi> formerly nominal King thereof, after whoſe death that Land alſo was by King <hi>Henrie</hi> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99021:11"/>third, granted to <hi>Richard de Burgo,</hi> heir to <hi>William,</hi> except the <hi>Cantreds</hi> of <hi>Roſcomon, Randon,</hi> and two or three other <hi>Cantreds</hi> neer <hi>Athlon;</hi> All which were after granted by ſucceeding Kings to other <hi>Engliſh,</hi> onely <hi>Roſcomon</hi> remained in the Crown, till Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> granted the ſame to one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Malby;</hi> This whole Countrie came after to the Crown, by the marriage of <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> ſon to King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, with the Daughter and heir of <hi>de Burgo;</hi> To S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Thomas Clare</hi> of the ſtock of the Earl of <hi>Glocester,</hi> all <hi>Ghomond,</hi> now the Countie of <hi>Clare</hi> which was confirmed to the ſame Familie, by grant from King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, to <hi>Robert le Poer,</hi> all the Countie of <hi>Waterford</hi> (except the Citie and cantred about it) the chief of the Familie, of which <hi>Poers</hi> is now a Baron; to <hi>Otho de Grandiſon</hi> all Tipperarie.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards King <hi>John</hi> having intelligence, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> began to bee at variance amongſt themſelvs, by reaſon that the Laws were not ſo ſpread, and adminiſtred as they ſhould bee, made a voiage in perſon thither, with a competent force for his honor and ſafetie, and then did hee divide the whole Land into Counties, as they for the moſt part ſtand at this daie, though <hi>Connaght</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster</hi> ſince are much ſubdivided, hee carried over with him divers learned men for civil and eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Notion, hee ordered and eſtabliſhed the Courts of Juſtice, as in <hi>England, viz.</hi> the Chancerie, the Kings Bench, Common Pleas, and Exchequer, and other Eccleſiaſtical Judicatures, and ſetled competent Judges in them; hee appointed Juſtices Itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and all other Officers for Law and execution of Juſtice; and four tearms in the year to bee kept as in <hi>England,</hi> by which the people became ſubject to Law (the <hi>Iriſh</hi> beeing ſtill held as enemies and Aliens) were better governed, lived in peace and great proſperitie manie years, ſave what ruptures it endured by their own diſſentions, as hereafter appeareth. So as by what is above ſpecified, it appear's the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were made lawfully inheritable, and became poſſeſſed of the whole conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, whereſoever they could finde places anie waie fit for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation; And to prove their poſſeſſions as well as their grants, beſides that in all the ancient Records, taking cognizance of all the habitable parts of that Land, in which thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99021:11"/>are named, you ſhall finde no Juries upon Inquiries, or trial of anie cauſes whatſoever, Capital, Criminal, or common, where is mentioned anie <hi>Iriſh</hi> name, but all <hi>Engliſh:</hi> All their Officers and Miniſters of Juſtice beeing the ſame, and beſide ſeveral Statute-Laws do aſſert their univerſal poſſeſſion. It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably evident, that generally all the now Freeholders of ſeveral great continents in that Iſland are <hi>Engliſh,</hi> either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendents, or deriving from thoſe firſt adventurers, or by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient grants from the Crown upon their forfeitures, though the truth is, manie of their laborers, underfarmers and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, which they call Churls, are and ſtill were <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the territories and Countries which thoſe <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſom of late ſettlement did, and do poſſeſs, are, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Down,</hi> the Countries of little <hi>Ards,</hi> the <hi>Duffrey, Lecale, Mourn,</hi> the <hi>Newrie,</hi> and ſeveral other places of leſſer note; all the Countie of <hi>Lowth,</hi> the whole Countie of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the entire Countie of <hi>Meath;</hi> the beſt and greateſt part of the Countie of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> all the Countie of <hi>Kildare,</hi> the greateſt and beſt part of the Countie of <hi>Catberlagh,</hi> part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Wickloe,</hi> the greateſt and beſt part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Wexford,</hi> all the Countie of <hi>Waterford,</hi> the greateſt and beſt part of the great Countie of <hi>Cork,</hi> the greateſt and beſt part of the Countie of <hi>Limerick,</hi> a great part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Kerrie,</hi> the better half of the Countie of <hi>Tipperary,</hi> all the Countie of <hi>Kilkennie,</hi> all the Countie of <hi>Galwaie,</hi> a good part of the Countie of <hi>Roſcomon,</hi> the moſt part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Maye,</hi> beſides the large territories of <hi>Leix</hi> and <hi>Ophalie,</hi> in the Queen's Countie, and King's Countie, planted in Queen <hi>Maries,</hi> and the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> Reigns, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rebellion of the <hi>Mores,</hi> and <hi>Conners,</hi> the ſurnames of theſe old <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſo manie (as of manie hundreds more can here bee remembred) are annexed towards the end of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the firſt <hi>Quere.</hi> Of theſe ſirnames manie are ſpread into verie numerous Families, and perſons, of which manie are advanced to degrees of Honor, and verie manie poſſeſſed of great eſtates; and further to prove that thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> were ſo poſſeſſed of all thoſe Lands, King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond, and ſom other ſucceeding Kings granted unto manie of thoſe Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99021:12"/>Countie <hi>Palatines,</hi> and unto manie other verie large Franchiſes and immunities, for the better ordering of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies:</hi> thoſe Adventurers divided the Lands generally into Mannors, particular Freeholds, and other <hi>Engliſh</hi> holdings; which (for the moſt part) do ſo continue to this daie; they granted all thoſe Lands for eaſie rents and ſervices to their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militants, except ſom ſmall parts which they kept in their own hands, who, or others deriving from them, do ſtill hold the ſame, <hi>pro parte conquestus,</hi> as generally appear's in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidences.</p>
                  <p>Yet further, to prove the <hi>Engliſh</hi> great and general poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there; it is an apparent and unqueſtionable truth, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and ſtrangers onely did build all the Caſtles, and ſtone-buildings, which then, and for ſom hundreds of years after, were to bee ſeen in anie part of that Iſland, neither had the <hi>Iriſh</hi> anie ſtone buildings of their own erecting, till about the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth, when ſom of them gained eſtates from the Crown, howbeit it is related in Hiſtorie, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> built Caſtles from Sea to Sea, beeing enjoined thereto by Law, beſide what was don by Kings, great Lords, and other principal adventurers.</p>
                  <p>It is further true, that all the Cities, Towns, and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions throughout that Land, are entirely <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and onely and originally endowed with Charters, Franchiſes and Lands by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> And howſoever ſom of the Maritim towns were at firſt planted (as is traditioned from the Ancients) by <hi>Owſtmen</hi> or <hi>Eaſterlings,</hi> who fully ſubmitted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law, (not ſuffering anie <hi>Iriſh</hi> to dwell amongſt them) yet thoſe firſt Inhabitants were after either ſo retracted or ſo worne out, as the Inhabitants became wholly <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as they undoubtedly remained till the reign of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth, and are for the moſt part hitherto the ſame, where they have not in ſom parts of <hi>Ireland</hi> been ruined, and corrupted by <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellions and inſurrections.</p>
                  <p>It is true likewiſe, that all the bridges and paſſages were built and made onely by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of old, and of late by the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> autoritie; And alſo that all Monaſteries, Religious Houſes, and Churches of anie good ſtructure were founded, built and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99021:12"/>endowed by the Engliſh, only ſom few deſpicable Cels of <hi>Monks</hi> there were, and ſome few poor Chappels diſpiſed, ſpecially in ſome poore Iſlands thereof.</p>
                  <p>Theſe being evident demonſtrations of the univerſall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Engliſh in that Iſland, it is further verified by ſome of their Laws in that Land wherein mention is made of beautifull Cities and Townes, planted by the Engliſh in that Iſland, but deſtroyed by Iriſh Commotions and garboils.</p>
                  <p>And more particularly by the Statute of <hi>Abſentees in tempore Henrie</hi> 8 and other Statutes, wherein are expreſſions declaring the tranquillitie and good order of the Engliſh in that Land, that the Engliſh long defended it in due ſubjection, againſt the Iriſh enemies.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo much to be obſerved, that it is not to be ſeen, before the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8 That the Iriſh had either Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, evidence or authentick writings for any Lands or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, neither could they have Intereſt, they being no other till then, but enemies and Aliens, neither had they diſtinctions or degrees of honor or Gentrie, neither Armenor other Enfigns or Officers of honours or gentrie, as Duke, Marqueſs, Earl, Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, Baron, Knight of any Order, Eſquire, or Gentleman, till the Engliſh introduced them, neither had they Governors of any legal or orderlie form, or Judges or Officers of any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Law or judicial courſ, neither had they Migiſtrates of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Cities, Burroughs or other Corporations or Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, or ſeals either of Juſtice or honour, or other ſpecies of civil or certain Reglement.</p>
                  <p>And to give you theſe truths, of the ancient and modern right and poſſeſſion of the <hi>Britains</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> in and to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (ſomwhat further ratified in all the parts of intereſt in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and dependence) it appear's by good antiquities that long before the entrance of <hi>William,</hi> the <hi>Norman,</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> the Arch-Biſhops of <hi>Canterburie</hi> had primacie over all <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the Biſhops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the ancient uſage and cuſtome, (as is written) received their conſecrations from the Metropolitan of <hi>England,</hi> it being declared in the time of the ſaid King <hi>William</hi> and his Son, that <hi>Canterburie</hi> was the Mother Church of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other Iſlands adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99021:13"/>(there being no Arch-Biſhops in <hi>Ireland,</hi> till about the yeer 1152. In juſtification of what is before premiſed, it is recorded, that <hi>Gotherick</hi> one of the pettie Kings in <hi>Ireland,</hi> did write to <hi>Lanfrank</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> for conſecration to be granted, to <hi>Patrick,</hi> nominated for a Biſhoprick: Alſo that the ſaid <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Lanfrank,</hi> out of his authoritie there, did write to <hi>Thurdel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack,</hi> another pettie King there, wherein he laie's to their charge, <hi>That the Iriſh men at their pleaſure did forſake their wedded wives without canonicall cauſ, and match with any others, even ſuch as were neer a kin to themſelvs or their abandoned wives, and that if an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man with like wickedneſs, caſt off a Wife, her alſo raſhly, and hand over head, they joined withal by lawes</hi> of <hi>marriage, or rather for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, an abuſe worthy to be puniſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo that <hi>Murchertagh</hi> another pettie King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Citizens of <hi>Waterford</hi> addreſſed to <hi>Anſelmus</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, Anno Dom.</hi> 1095. for erecting and ordaining at <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> a Biſhop, where no Biſhop had been, and for conſecrating a Biſhop there, whoſe name was <hi>Malchus,</hi> hee alſo wrot for conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another to be Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> much about the ſame time; alſo that the Citizens of <hi>Dublin</hi> ſent <hi>Gregorie</hi> (choſen to bee Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop there) unto <hi>Ralph Arch-Biſhop of Canterburie,</hi> ſuing to him in theſe words, <hi>viz. Anteceſſorum veſtrorum magiſterio, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Maſterſhip or chief rule of your Anceſtors, wee willingly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our Prelats, from which (wee remember) that our Prelats have received their eccleſiasticall dignities, &amp;c.</hi> All which, and other applications of like nature, doe cleerly evince the ſubmiſſion of the Iriſh Clergie, to the rule and ſuperintendencie of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> their then acknowledged <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to proceed yet a little further, to prove the antient Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Title to <hi>Ireland: In the Statute of the</hi> 11. <hi>Reginae Elizabethae, for granting lands in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter to that Queen, her heirs and Succeſſors;</hi> It is declared, <hi>That the Crown of England had ancient and authentick Titles to the State and poſſeſsion of the Land of Ireland, conveied farr beyond the linage of the Iriſh.</hi> Alſo By a Statute <hi>tempore Philippi &amp; Mariae, for veſting the two large Territories of Leix and Ophalie in the Crowne:</hi> It is there again declared, <hi>That the Crown of England had good right thereunto before, and that the Iriſh had entred into thoſe lands
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99021:13"/>by force, and wrongfully uſurped the poſſeſsion thereof,</hi> Which Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes were enacted by the immediate Anceſtors of that ſuppoſed Nation now in Rebellion; the one made under a Popiſh Prince, the other under a Proteſtant, Other Statutes and Records make like mention of the antient right of <hi>England,</hi> to the Land of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and where there is mention above made of about one hundred yeers quiet poſſeſſion of the Engliſh over all that Iſland, in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and after, it may be demanded how afterwards thoſe deſpicable Iriſh ſo gain'd upon the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, as in ſomtimes they did, and how they obtained ſuch large poſſeſſions, as in later times they had: A cleer and obvious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all that well know <hi>Ireland</hi> may be given, That thoſe Engliſh Lords Adventurers, having <hi>jura Regalia,</hi> and other great priviledges, and authorities within their Counties Palatine (being eight in number at one time) and therein power to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, make Chancellors, Barons and Knights, to make Judges, Sheriffs, and all Officers within themſelvs (the Kings having few Sheriffs any where, except in the <hi>Croſſes</hi> or <hi>Tipperarie</hi> in <hi>Mounſter,</hi> neither was there much Law executed by the Kings immediate Authoritie) thoſe Lords received great yeerlie reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, and ſome of them often advanced to the government of that Land, by the King's favour, the Colonies under them being rich, and ſpread all over the Land. Thoſe Lords being com to the height of proſperitie, and not able wiſely to manage and applie to their own good, thoſe great powers, endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Graces of their Kings, fell into jealouſies and emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations one againſt another, whereupon enſued ſharp and bloudie contentions, they having power to make peace and warr at pleaſure, without the licenſ or authority of their chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors (which power was afterwards taken away by ſeveral ſtatutes) they entred into ſundrie violences one againſt another, and combined Parties againſt Parties; to maintain which, they called in to their Aſſiſtance, their known enemies, the Iriſh, (then grown up into ſom numbers) and ſo farr were they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with their blind envious ſurie that they put Arms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Iriſh and conducted them to their battails as hired Souldiers: they aſſumed power to lay Taxes, Ceſſes, and Impoſitions upon their Engliſh Colonies, Tenants, and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99021:14"/>and by that meanes ſupported both their Engliſh and Iriſh Soldiers, to the oppreſſion of the other Engliſh, but Lords countenancing and ſtrengthning of the Iriſh, beſides training them in Martiall actions. Theſe diſſentions and animoſities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the reign of King <hi>John,</hi> as is before touched, but they roſe not to much virulence, till towards the end of the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, and ſo continued by fits in the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, as that King's greater actions in <hi>France, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> averted him from the more ſpecial care of that Common-wealth; they conflicted in this manner many times, one againſt another, to the great conſumption of their Engliſh Tenants, who ſerved under them, as the <hi>Lacies</hi> of <hi>Meath</hi> warred againſt <hi>Courcie</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> the foreſaid <hi>Lacies</hi> after, againſt the <hi>Bourks</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> and <hi>Connaght,</hi> the foreſaid <hi>Lacies</hi> againſt the <hi>Marſhals</hi> of <hi>Leimſter,</hi> who held that Countrie in right of the daughter &amp; heir of the bovſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> of <hi>Stigil,</hi> married to <hi>Marſhal:</hi> The <hi>Garaldines</hi> of <hi>Mounſter &amp; Leimſter</hi> againſt the <hi>Butlers,</hi> the <hi>Garaldines</hi> againſt the <hi>Bourks,</hi> the <hi>Bourks,</hi> againſt the <hi>Verdons</hi> of <hi>Meath,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lowth;</hi> the <hi>Bourks</hi> againſt the <hi>Clares;</hi> the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minghams</hi> againſt the <hi>Verdons</hi> and other Engliſh in the <hi>Pale:</hi> The <hi>Garaldines, Butlers,</hi> and <hi>Briminghams</hi> againſt the <hi>Bourks</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and indeed all the Engliſh Progenies, by part-taking and private Offences given, and taken, were imbroiled in the ſame quarrels, the Iriſh looking on, and ſiding whereſoever they thought beſt, ſtriving by their cunning and malicious inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to enlarge and blow everie ſpark of diſcord amongſt them into flames of hoſtilitie: Hereupon ſtart up that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and wicked cuſtom of <hi>Coigne</hi> and <hi>Liverie,</hi> which was horſ-meat, mans-meat, and money taken by the Soldiers upon the Colonies, and Engliſh Inhabitants, which cuſtom and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, was afterwards by ſome Statutes made Felonie, and by other Satutes made treaſon, one whereof hath this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Viz. At the requeſt and ſupplication of the Commons of this Land of Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Whereas of long time there hath been uſed &amp; exacted by the Lords and Gentlemen of this Land, many and divers damnable cuſtoms and uſages, which have been called Coigne and Liverie, that is, horſ-meat and mans-meat, for finding their Horſ-men and Foot-men, and over that four-pence a day for every of them, to be had and paid, of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99021:14"/>the poot earth-tillers and tenants, inhabitants of the ſame Land, without anie thing doing, or paying for the ſame, beſides mante Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, murthers, rapes, and other manifold extortions and oppreſſions by the ſaid horſmen and footmen, daily and nightly committed and don, which bee the principal cauſes of the deſolation and deſtruction of the ſaid Land, and hath brought the ſame into ruine and decaie, ſo as moſt part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Freeholders and tenants have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted thereof, ſom into the realm of</hi> England, <hi>and ſom into other strange Lands; Whereupon the aforeſaid Lords and Gentlemen have intruded into the ſaid Freeholders and tenants inheritances, and the ſame kept and occupied as their own, and ſet under them in the ſame Lands the King's Iriſh enemies, to the diminiſhing of holy Church-rights, the diſheriſon of the King and his obedient Subjects, and the utter ruine and deſolation of the Land; For Reformation whereof, bee it enacted, &amp;c.</hi> By this and manie other like Laws, it is apparent, how the <hi>Iriſh</hi> thruſt themſelvs into great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Land, and afterwards as in the ſequel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, made themſelvs owners of them; Another waie of their entrance was by frauduent force and incurſion, as when by theſe broils one <hi>Colonie</hi> had ruined another, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> (bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in favor with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords by their deceitful ſervice) ſeized upon the weaker <hi>Colonie,</hi> and forced out the inhabitants, which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords allowed of for the time, receiving the <hi>Iriſh</hi> as tenants at will, (though they afterwards turned the Lord's themſelvs quite out) Becauſ the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would ſeem to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford far greater rents, then the old Britiſh Freeholder, and alſo yeild for the time more Subjection, and (baſely) alſo they committed their goods, eſtates, wives, and children, to the will of thoſe Lords (as formerly, and afterwards they did to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Chieftains) another waie of their entrance was, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords (now ſtrangely degenerating, and taking liking to their licentious, ſordid, and barbarous courſ of liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) made them manie times their Officers in their Countries, as <hi>Seneſhals, Marſhals,</hi> and other Officers, (becauſ they would ſlaviſhly obeie their wills, who by extortion and oppreſſion, in ſhort time forced out the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tenants, and in after times held the land as their own, againſt the verie Lords.</p>
                  <p>The wideſt Inlet they found, was about the tenth year of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99021:15"/>King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, when <hi>Edward Bruice</hi> brother to the King of <hi>Scots</hi> entered into <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> with a power of <hi>Scots,</hi> (ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to bee ſix thouſand) and there committed great ſlaughter of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> both men, women and children; Theſe gave one overthrew to <hi>Richard de Burgo,</hi> or <hi>Bourk,</hi> and at another time took <hi>William de Burgo</hi> brother to <hi>Richard,</hi> priſoner; they ruined Towns, Caſtles, houſes and Churches, whereſoever they came, and upon theſe events, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> there (who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly durſt little ſhew themſelvs, living in the leaſt habitable parts by ſufferance of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) roſe and joined with the <hi>Scots,</hi> making all the deſtruction they could of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> with this addition <hi>Edward Bruice</hi> proceeded further, through the parts of <hi>Leimſter</hi> (the <hi>Iriſh</hi> from all parts gathering to him) and from thence marched into <hi>Mounſter,</hi> as far as <hi>Caſhel,</hi> then did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> lift up their heads on all ſides, following the train of <hi>Bruice,</hi> ſpoiling and deſtroying the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as far as they could; then the ſaid <hi>Bruice</hi> finding that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> began to aſſemble in ſom numbers againſt him, retired into the lower parts of <hi>Meath</hi> (now <hi>Weſtmeath</hi>) and to the borders of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> making it his Maſter-work to ſecure that Province within his own power, (though hee often made roads into other parts) which is the firſt cauſ and ground why <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> became ſo deſtitute of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and grew wholly <hi>Iriſh,</hi> beyond anie other of the Provinces; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> beeing as zealous as hee to rid themſelvs ſolely of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> In this poſture hee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued about three years in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and cauſed himſelf to bee proclaimed King by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and about the end of the ſaid three years, making an expedition to invade the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the <hi>Pale,</hi> hee was in the Countie of <hi>Lowth</hi> encountered by <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingham</hi> (after created Earl of <hi>Lowth</hi>) and other good forces of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Bruice,</hi> and manie of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders were ſlain, and his Armie totally defeated and rent; Som of the <hi>Scots</hi> returned home, but manie remained there who joined with the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> in that time the ſaid <hi>Bruice,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had much diſpeopled, and forced moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of the Limits and Countries now called the Counties of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagal, Fermanagh, Cavan, Tirone, Londonderry, Monorghan</hi> and <hi>Ardmagh</hi> having ſealed their malice by much devaſtation alſo,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99021:15"/>within the Countries of <hi>Autrim</hi> and <hi>Down,</hi> lying between the Sea on the Eaſt, and the great <hi>Lough</hi> called <hi>Lough Eaugh,</hi> and the River of <hi>Baun</hi> in the Weſt, hardly acceſſible by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> yet did <hi>William de Burgo</hi> hold up a face of power in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster</hi> by help of other neighbouring <hi>Engliſh,</hi> until about the ſeventh year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, when hee was amongſt them murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, leaving onely an heir female, who after married with <hi>Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> third ſon to King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, ſoon after the death of the ſaid <hi>William, Hugh ô Neil</hi> taking upon him ſuperioritie amongſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> (now grown ſtrong through the actions of <hi>Bruice,</hi> and the decaie of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) adventured to break over the <hi>Ban,</hi> and made great havock in the <hi>Colonies</hi> of the Rowt <hi>Clandebois, Ardes,</hi> and others within that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite, who in truth, never in anie degree of their former bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recovered themſelvs after; and thus you ſee in a manner the full ruine of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter.</hi> Another enlargement gained by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> men's Lands, was ſoon after the departure of <hi>Bruice</hi> out of <hi>Mounſter,</hi> when <hi>Morrice Fitz-Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Garaldine</hi> of <hi>Deſmond,</hi> having taken into his alliance and ſervice manie of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> made eruption into the Counties of <hi>Kerry, Limerick, Cork,</hi> and part of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and in ſhort time deſtroied and baniſhed great parts of thoſe <hi>Colonies,</hi> and there placed his followers (more <hi>Iriſh</hi> then <hi>Engliſh</hi>) and forced moſt of the reſt to join, or ſubmit to his will; Soon after did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> upon the <hi>Shanon</hi> ſide advance themſelvs, and ſetled in the large Countrie of <hi>Ormond in Tipperary,</hi> then entirely the inheritance of the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> (by acquiſition of his anceſtors) whereof ſom ſmall parts were after recovered by the ſucceeding Earls of <hi>Ormond,</hi> which now they hold, the reſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> paying ſom ſmall acknowledgment by compoſition.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> alſo then entred into ſeveral other Wood-land Countries in <hi>Tipperary,</hi> whence terrifying and forcing out the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they ſeated themſelvs there. About the end of the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond (in the abſence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords of <hi>Leimſter, Donald</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Art Covenagh</hi> a baſtard branch of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot ne Gall,</hi> late reputed King of <hi>Leimſter</hi> (ſo called in the <hi>Welſh,</hi> and other <hi>Iriſh</hi> of thoſe parts) brake out, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broiled
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99021:16"/>thoſe <hi>Clonies,</hi> renting from them great parts of the Wood lands and mountainous Countries, ſoon after <hi>Liſagh Moor,</hi> and one of the <hi>Conners</hi> in the heart of <hi>Leimſter,</hi> diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered themſelvs in open enmitie; The ſaid <hi>Liſagh</hi> (taking eight Caſtles in one evening by ſurprize) defaced the Caſtle of <hi>Donamaſe,</hi> the Earl of <hi>March</hi> his chief houſ in <hi>Leix,</hi> and upon the ruining of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe Countries, the one called himſelf <hi>ô Moor,</hi> Lord of <hi>Leix,</hi> and the other <hi>ô Conner,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ophalie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the death of the ſaid <hi>William de Burgo,</hi> above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, certain of the moſt active men of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in <hi>Connaght,</hi> joining with ſom degenerate branches of the <hi>Bourks</hi> (who had formerly aſſiſted in the deſtroying, and rooting out of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in the Southern parts of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> next unto <hi>Connaght</hi>) entered into all the goodly poſſeſſions of the ſaid <hi>William,</hi> in <hi>Connaght,</hi> expelled the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and made themſelvs Maſters of all; One of the ſaid <hi>Bourks</hi> ſeating himſelf in the Countie of <hi>Galway</hi> (of whom is deſcended the Earl of <hi>Clanrickard,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other faſtned himſelf in the Countie of <hi>Mayo;</hi> and both took upon them <hi>Iriſh</hi> Captain-ſhips; the one by the name M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>William Eighter,</hi> and the other by the name of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>William Oughter,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining with them manie of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to inhabit the Land, and fully finiſh the extirpation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Freeholders, the reſt of the <hi>Iriſh Partiſans</hi> fell into the more northern parts of <hi>Connaght,</hi> as the Counties of <hi>Sligo</hi> and <hi>Leitrim,</hi> and alſo the Northern parts of the Countie of <hi>Roſcomon,</hi> who ſo fully accompliſhed the expulſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as in the time of King <hi>Charls,</hi> an intention beeing to plant that Province) upon Inquirie made into everie particular man's holding, there could not bee ſhewed anie antient Evidence for anie Land holden amongſt them, as in the other Provinces of <hi>Mounſter</hi> and <hi>Leimſter,</hi> are to bee ſhewed in great numbers.</p>
                  <p>About the twentie fifth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, was <hi>Richard de Clare</hi> murthered by the men of <hi>Thomond,</hi> at what time, and after, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſo inſulted there, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were either in ſhort time maſſacred, or forced into other parts for their more ſafetie:</p>
                  <p>And thus is plainly evidenced in brief, part of the means of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99021:16"/>the great incroachments of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, eſpecially in the remote parts, and now were the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords, and ſuch of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Freeholders as they could draw or force with them, arrived at a great height of degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Now had they for the moſt part betaken themſelvs to the <hi>Brehan</hi> or <hi>Taniſtree</hi> Law, as they called it, and other <hi>Iriſh</hi> uſages and cuſtoms (ſo deſtructive to themſelvs) and repudiated the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws brought with them, under which they happily lived, and under which the people of <hi>England</hi> had, and have ſo manie ages floriſhed, and been famous through providence, except what remained in the five ſhiers of the <hi>Pale,</hi> and in ſom ſmall circuits about the walled-Towns, which reteined in ſom meaſure the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws: Now did they generally em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the <hi>Iriſh</hi> garb of licentiouſnes and tyrannie over the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors; They erected amongſt themſelvs Captain-ſhips in their Countries, after the <hi>Iriſh</hi> faſhion, and unwiſely ſuffered the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to do the like, where they had gotten footing, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauding them in all things, whereby the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were raiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a kinde of Dominion; they little obeied or regarded the Governors ſent out of <hi>England</hi> (though for their onely good, and manie times to reſcue them from the <hi>Iriſh</hi> outrages and furie, and reconcile their own unnatural jars) they ſuffered not the King's Writs to run in their Countries, but they would undertake in a ſummarie waie, to anſwer for their followers, as they now call them, for what wrong or crime ſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; they aſſumed <hi>Iriſh</hi> nicknames, as the chief of the <hi>Burks,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>William Brimingham,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Yoris Mangle,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Coſtelo Dexeter,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Jorden Archdeacon,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Odo Condon,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Maiog,</hi> one of the <hi>Garaldines,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Gibbon,</hi> and ſom hundreds the like in that Land, and this they did in contempt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> name and Nation; They went to the wars in <hi>Iriſh</hi> furniture to their horſes, and <hi>Iriſh</hi> arms defenſive and offenſive, ſhearing their horſes mains after the <hi>Iriſh</hi> manner: Inſomuch, as afterwards there was neceſſitie by Laws to enforce them to ride in ſaddles; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> riding onely on ſmall quilted pillions, faſtned one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a ſurſingle; they combined in ſull complacencie for courſ of life with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in all things, even to rebellious actions, ſeveral times, yea, ſo far were they ſunck in this baſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99021:17"/>degeneration and defection, as the Earl of <hi>Deſmond claimed privilege, never to com to Parlament, or within walled Town, but at his own pleaſure,</hi> (which privilege hee in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time ſurrendred and renounced) And it was reſolved amongſt them, that becauſ they by violence and oppreſſion had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded into the Lands of the inferior <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and given the <hi>Iriſh</hi> libertie to dwell there firſt <hi>at will,</hi> (though it proved otherwiſe after) and finding the power out of <hi>England</hi> ſlack to controul them, by reaſon of other imploiments; They at length judged it moſt preſervative to incorporate with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and ſo caſt off the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law and Loialtie, preſuming thereby, the better to keep what they had ſo raviſhed, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, that if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law gained concurrencie amongſt them, the parties wronged, or their deſcendents removed as aforeſaid, would (doubtles) recover their own, and ſo ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the great <hi>revenues and cuttings,</hi> wherein they thought they had aſcertained a compleat intereſt, by thoſe waies of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; But it fell out otherwiſe in ſhor time, for by God's juſt avengement on their wickedneſs, the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (who manie years lived in the Iſland as aforeſaid, by their ſufferance, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of force, nor anie waie deterred by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> daily increaſing in numbers, actuated in Martial Diſcipline, poſſeſſed alſo (though but at will, of great quantities of Land) they, as opportunities offered, (part whereof is after herein expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) roſe up againſt their Lords, eſpecially in the Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Countries, and called the Lands their own; and in ſhort time became formidable to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who began now to finde their error, in ſo prodigiouſly forgetting themſelvs, their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anceſtors and originals, and the glorious Kingdom from whence they came, putting themſelvs, in a manner, into the hands of their ſlaviſh enemies, and (as may bee ſaid) were transformed into another people: Theſe diſorders, fractures, and inſolencies, and the great preſſures and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> crying loud into <hi>England,</hi> at laſt the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and victorious Prince, King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, pitying their deformed and lapſed condition, in the thirtie ſixth year of his reign (though his forrein engagements were great and heavie at that time) ſent thither as his Lieutenant, <hi>Lionel Duke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99021:17"/>of Clarence</hi> his third ſon above mentioned, with a competent ſtrength, to reduce things to ſome better form; this young Lord continued there (for the moſt part) ſeven yeers, brought with him a good and honorable Council, both for peace and warr, ſet himſelf with all zeal and affection, ſpecially to reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Engliſh Colonies, if it might be, to reintegrate them in their priſtin eſtates, freedom and government, himſelf having good intereſt there as is above touched. To this Livetenant manie of the Iriſh made ſubmiſsions, as they had manie times don before to King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond, King <hi>John,</hi> and after to King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and others, authoriſed by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> he had ſundrie conflicts with the Iriſh, verie manie of the Engliſh (after a ſhort time) ſiding with him.</p>
                  <p>About the 40 yeer of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, he held that famous Parlament at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> wherein plainly appear's (by the Lawes made there, and ſom others formerly enacted by <hi>Rockeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Ireland</hi> 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3) the great degeneration and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the old Engliſh above ſpecified (Laws and Statutes being the beſt Dictates of the maladies of times) and that the principal labour was to reform, and bring into temper and rule of Law, the old Engliſh Colonies, Som particulars of which Laws were, <hi>viz. Againſt Parlies with the Iriſh without leave; That Chieftains ſhould aſſiſt and apprehend Felons; Againſt barbarous Fees and extortions of the Lord's Officers called Marſhals; Againſt the Engliſh calling the Iriſh to help them in their quarrels; Againſt the Lords diſtreining contrarie to the Engliſh Law; That the Engliſh ſhould only uſe the Engliſh Law, and not the cuſtom called the Brehan Law, or Marcheor Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That if anie of the Engliſh race, ſhould uſe an Iriſh name, Iriſh lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Iriſh apparrel, or anie other guiſe or faſhion of the Iriſh, his Lands ſhould bee ſeiſed till hee conformed, Or (if he no Land) then other mulcts were appointed; That the Lords ſhould not diſturb the King's Officers in executing their Offices; That Serjeants Bailiffs ſhould exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the commands of the King and of the Sheriffs, that the Sheriffs and Serjeants of Franchiſes, ſhould give acquittances for the Kings money received of Debtors, and receiv and pay by Indenture: That no She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs ſhould hold Courts contrarie to the Common Law; That the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99021:18"/>ſhould not marrie, nor Goſſip with the Iriſh; That the Engliſh ſhould uſe the Engliſh language and nurture; That old and new Engliſh ſhould all alike be called Lieges of the King; That no Engliſh ſhould uſe Iriſh or barbarous ſports; that no Iriſh Pipers, Rimers, bablers, Ske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laghs, Ferdanes, Carraghs or news-tellers, ſhould bee ſuffered to com a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Engliſh: That no Kearns, Hoblers, nor idle men ſhould range, take meat, &amp;c, of the people againſt their wills, but hue and crie to be made after them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That no Iriſh ſhould be admitted to benefits, or entred into religious houſes: That Judges ſhould travel half yeerly to enquire of offences, and to execute the Law: That four Juſtices of peace, of and in each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould charge the Inhabitants with horſ and foot to defend themſelvs againſt Iriſh enemies. That robberies committed in the guildable, ſhould not be protected in the franchiſes, and ſo on the contrarie, but the theeves to be delivered up to the proper officers;</hi> and many other like Laws, were then made towards reſtauration, and recompoſing of the then deformed and adulterated Engliſh; and for the further redreſs, divers other Laws (ſom before, and ſom after) were made, <hi>viz. One to take away protections, which with frequent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons were obſerved to be peſtilent Remora's to the Engliſh reſtitution and ſecure peace,</hi> inſomuch as King <hi>Edward the third,</hi> towards the later end of his reign, ſent two Ordinances into <hi>Ireland, viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Juſtitiarius Hiberniae non concedat pardonationes de morte hominis, nec de roberiis, ſeu incendiis, et quòd de caetero certificet domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Regem de nominibus petentium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Item quòd nec Juſtitiarius, nec aliquis magnas Hiber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, concedat protectiones alicui contra pacem regis exiſtentis.</hi> And the experience of the common dammage by ſuch pardons, and protections ever ſince, prove's the malignancie of them, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing charged by divers good authors (converſant in Iriſh affairs) to be the diſhonour and ruine of the Common-wealth: Other Laws were alſo made, <hi>viz. One to diſtinguiſh betwixt the Engliſh and Iriſh, by the cutting off their beards:</hi> Another, <hi>againſt the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of amends for the murther of a friend:</hi> Another <hi>That no man ſhould ſtirr up the Iriſh to aſſiſt in their warr:</hi> Another, <hi>Againſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Theeves into Comerick</hi> (in Engliſh) <hi>protection:</hi> All which Laws at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> were after confirmed, and revived by another Law made in the tenth yeer of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeventh Chap. 8, Wherein are theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> As long as thoſe Laws were
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99021:18"/>put in ure and execution, this Land continued in proſperitie and honor, and ſince they were not executed, the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled and digreſſed from their obedience, and the Land fell to ruine and deſolation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the truth is, it appear's by good Hiſtories of thoſe times, and more authentically by Records, both of the Exchequer &amp; Common-pleas of thoſe yeers, that by practice of theſe Lawes, and the induſtrie &amp; travel of the ſaid <hi>Lionel,</hi> notable alteration was made, in the manners of the people, and much don of value towards the reſtitution of the Engliſh Government, in the Engliſh Colonies; That the Crown-Revenues, both certain and caſuall, were duly accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for in all the Provinces, and that the King's Writ did run, &amp; the Common-Law executed in all parts amongſt the Engliſh.</p>
                  <p>This Duke built the wals of <hi>Catherlagh,</hi> hee alſo reduced much lands in <hi>Connaght</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> into the Engliſh mens hands, and this good order continued all the reſidue of that King's reign, and part of the reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, but towards the middle of his time, the Iriſh and ſom farr degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Engliſh, hearing of the Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> his death in <hi>Italie,</hi> and finding great diſſentions to ariſe in <hi>England,</hi> combined themſelvs to the freſh annoiance of the Engliſh, and proſecuting their long intendment to exſtirpate them: And now did the Engliſh finde cauſ to raiſ themſelvs into defenſ againſt the Iriſh, which they were afterwards dangerouſly put unto: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that King having received repulſ in his affectation to bee Emperor, and deſirous to act ſomthing of glorie, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his people, about the 18 yeer of his reign, undertook a roial expedition into <hi>Ireland,</hi> tranſporting with him 30000 foot, and 4000 men at Arms, as the Chronicles relate, whereat the Iriſh being terrified, fell into their old lock of ſubmiſſions (the verie gulf which hath hitherto ſwallowed up all the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaies and labors of reformation there) hoping thereby to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv that force, and fruſtrate his good deſign; and to inſiſt on the verie truth, that courſ of pardons upon ſubmiſſions of the Iriſh, hath for at leaſt three hundred yeers paſt, bottomed all the combuſtions and inſults of the Iriſh.</p>
                  <p>That King being not in caſe to be long abſent, was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to accept of their ſubmiſſions, which hee did from all the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99021:19"/>powerful men of the Iriſh, and ſom degenerate Engliſh Lords, thoſe Iriſh of <hi>Leimſter</hi> taking Oath to leav the Land to his free diſpoſe by a certain time.</p>
                  <p>Great quantities of the <hi>Leimſter</hi> land were granted to Sir <hi>John de Bellomonto,</hi> and others, whoſe iſſues long after enjoyed it, he alſo conditioned with the Iriſh of <hi>Connaght</hi> and <hi>Ulſter</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſubmiſſions, to reſtore the Lands to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> never performed: So this young Prince abuſed by the frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent ſubmiſſions of the Iriſh, (as others before, and after were) returned with his men into <hi>England,</hi> leaving the Engliſh in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in but a little better caſe then he found them: Soon after his departure the Iriſh brake forth, and ſtood up for their ends, as high as ever, whereupon enſued great conflicts between them and the Engliſh, in one of which was ſlain <hi>Mortimer</hi> Earl of <hi>March</hi> the King's Lievtenant; thereupon did many of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (overhaled with burthens and harrowings) relinquiſh their eſtates, and reſort into <hi>England,</hi> to ſide with Parties there, as their affections did lead them, though Lawes were in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Ordinances in <hi>England,</hi> as well to ſtop their going, as to return them back.</p>
                  <p>It is not recorded nor known (as is conceived) that in the reigns of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, or King <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifth, (who were much taken up in other buſineſs) any forces were ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereby the Iriſh inlarged much, partly through the departure of the Engliſh, and chiefly by the great devaſtations they formerly ſuffered, beſides what diminutions they endured by ſeveral Kings, tranſmitting great numbers of them to aſſiſt in the warrs of <hi>France, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times.</p>
                  <p>In the former part of the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Ireland</hi> continued In the ſame poſture; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> beeing now put to their defence in all parts, but the greateſt and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable decaie, and ruine of the proſperitie, and poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> began in the later end of the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt, and in the beginning of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth; For after the middle of the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt. <hi>Richard Duke of York</hi> beginning to whiſper his right to the Crown more audibly then before, hee was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99021:19"/>ſoon after ſent into <hi>Ireland Lievtenant,</hi> which was ſomtimes uſual, as a removal of ſuch as were dangerous, or pretended trouble; There hee had given him much regal autoritie more then might bee conſonant to right reaſon, had they well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the place, or the conſequences, hee was continued there nine or ten years by himſelf, and his Deputies, himſelf making ſtarts into <hi>England,</hi> which, as it was handled, ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his power in <hi>Ireland,</hi> hee had power to diſpoſe the King's revenues, as hee thought fit, hee had power to grant and let the King's Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to place and diſplace officers, and to wage what men hee thought good: This Lord (eſteemed there a perſon of high blood) having an eie more upon events in <hi>England,</hi> then the reducement of <hi>Ireland,</hi> applied himſelf for the moſt part towards his own pretentions, hee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained both parties, <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> in a plauſible waie, travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his ſecret thoughts to faſten parties to him, againſt the time hee might have uſe of them; Hee tolerated the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to hold what they had formerly intruded unto, not ſparing favors where hee obſerved reaſon to oblige, and they regarding ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what his high birth (a thing they ſeem moſt to adore) were by thoſe means held more quiet then in former times, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by courteſie and fair entreatie, and by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of imploiments, ſo as hee found great adherence by waie of perſonal affection, hee made ſom journies into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> always accompanied with ſom of the Gentrie of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to propagate and ripen confederacie; In <hi>England</hi> hee endured the changes of war; At laſt hee was forced into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where hee gather's more ſtrength, and hearing that <hi>Warwick</hi> and <hi>Salisburie</hi> had taken the King, hee com's over, attended with good numbers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords and others, and ſom of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Hee obtein's his ends in Parlament; The Queen flie's into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and coming back, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> meet's her at <hi>Wakefield,</hi> where hee was ſlain, and manie of thoſe of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with him; the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> on the other ſide, beeing a profeſſor to the houſ of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> paſſed into <hi>England</hi> about the ſame time, with manie of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſom <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the Earl of <hi>March</hi> encounter's him, and others at <hi>Mortimer's</hi> Croſs in <hi>Wales;</hi> there is <hi>Ormond</hi> and the reſt defeated; and manie of <hi>Ireland</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99021:20"/>ſlain: So as what by the companies which at times paſſed over with the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and what by ſuch as voluntarily led themſelvs into <hi>England,</hi> on both ſides, during thoſe combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, great conſumptions of thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> could not but bee the conſequent, eſpecially, the Gentrie and beſt men: Hereupon did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> on all ſides exſpatiate, and faſten upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſſions, where they could reach, and indeed in ſhort time ſo dilated themſelvs, as they for the time forced the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into their ſtrengths, and into narrow rooms; they confirmed themſelvs in their formerly erected and uſurped Captainſhips, which before the reign of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, were far to manie, and moſt of them ſo continued, till the end of the reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> therein exerciſing an abſolute tyrannical power over all inferiors, aſwell all ſuch <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> as hazarded to continue amongſt them, as the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> And here may the <hi>Queriſt,</hi> and all others take full view of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, foot-ſteps, and means of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> incroachments upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſſions, though it is true, that in after times manie of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> became repoſſeſſed of much of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Lands, except in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> and <hi>Connaght,</hi> in which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces manie of the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> are now as barbarous as the meer <hi>Iriſh,</hi> hardly to bee diſtinguiſhed; yet by what is above written, it grow's more lucid and cleer, that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that Iſland, who now ſtand in arms againſt <hi>England,</hi> (who in ſeveral ſucceſſions ſetled them there) are not ſuch an entire nation fixed there <hi>by God and Nature,</hi> free from anie other power and challenge, as the <hi>Queriſt</hi> propound's them, and where the entiretie of ſuch a Nation (footed there as is pretended) is to bee found, (as things are before diſcovered) will require a verie weariſom ſcrutinie, and at laſt ſatisfie no underſtanding man. Nay, it is avouched by ſeveral good writers, and may bee truly aſſerted in the experience of ſuch as well underſtand <hi>Ireland,</hi> that ſetting aſide the firſt Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants from Britain, and other Nations inſerted there by the permiſſion of the Britains, and ſuch as had power in Britain, and ſuch as of themſelvs intruded before the entrance of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond, promiſcuouſly laced amongſt them, who all now paſs under the Notion, and ſtyle of the old <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99021:20"/>verie <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſent in thither by King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond, and other Kings ſucceeding him before King <hi>James,</hi> and who at the beginning of this Rebellion were really ſtated, and veſted in Lands in that Iſland, (though not in numbers and bodies of men (becauſ moſt of the Churls, and laborers as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, were <hi>Iriſh</hi>) nor perhaps in quantities and extents of Lands, yet in true value and command, over others) did far exceed, and were far more eſtimable and powerful in that Iſland, then thoſe, denominated the old <hi>Iriſh,</hi> beſides the the great towns, which (as is above ſaid) are wholly, in a manner, <hi>Engliſh:</hi> for conſider their preſent compoſure of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and affairs, even after this late horrid and inhumane eradication of the new <hi>Engliſh</hi> and proteſtants:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Their Nobilitie (now in rebellion) are all old <hi>Engliſh</hi> except a verie few, which were, and yet are both weak in power and ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>Their ſupream Council (as they call it) and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, and Countie Councils, and their general Aſſemblie are for the moſt part old Engliſh, moſt of the beſt Commanders in the war are of the ſame; moſt of their horſ and manie of their foot, (who have been moſt daring in the Rebellion) are of the ſame; the whole frame of their new-Modelled-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was at firſt digeſted, and is ever ſince countenanced, and enlivened by the old Engliſh, they ſeem in their conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to put themſelvs for the moſt part (in waie of policie at preſent) into the frame of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws, becauſ they well know, how uncertain and barbarous their ſuppoſed <hi>Iriſh</hi> Laws were, (though verie manie of them rather deſire the old <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tyrannie, and rude exorbitancie) And were it not that the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> were, and ſtill are, that the bodie of their order and connexion, even apparently managing their whole par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as to war and Government, the reſt would ſoon diſſolv into their old <hi>Kearniſh</hi> habit, both in fight, and onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in bogs and woods; And which ſeem's moſt of amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this buſineſs, the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> (ſhewing themſelvs of late years in manie things, much more ſwelling and envious againſt the Proteſtant Religion, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government and converſation then the meer <hi>Iriſh</hi>) were the principal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers, and ripeners of this deſtable Rebellion, and Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99021:21"/>without whoſe incitement and flexible concurrence, (as <hi>Ireland</hi> at the begining of the Rebellion ſtood furniſhed with multitudes of new <hi>Engliſh</hi> in all parts, (except <hi>Connaght,</hi> where they were feweſt) and ſtrengthned with the old <hi>Engliſh,</hi> if they had ſtood loial to their own Nation, or really ſenſible of their own happineſs (as in nature and all prudence they ſhould have don) the <hi>Iriſh</hi> no waie durſt have entered upon ſuch an attempt againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Proteſtants, eſpecially a Parlament then ſitting in <hi>England,</hi> who they might well believ would ſo far diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte ſuch high and unparaleld Ravages, and horrible effuſion of bloud (without cauſ or provocation) committed upon ſom of their own fleſh and bloud, and alſo ſuch ſavage indignities of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, as that they would ſpeedily bend their power to redreſs and revenge the ſame; And yet it may bee conſidered, that the opportunitie of the attempt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> will not appear ſo ſtrange; when wee conſider their animation, and incouragement to have its riſe from manie of the Native Inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> of the ſame <hi>Religion</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, who made it their work to feel the pulſ, and finde the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of <hi>England</hi> to that end: And the Commiſſioners pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to ſecure the perſons and Eſtates of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> was to ſpeak effectively) to command them to deſtroie both, which (if not ſpeedily executed) might have exſpired or been rewaked upon diſcoverie, which is moſt obvious; it wee reflect upon the ſeveral journies of the popiſh partie of thoſe Agents imploied by the Parlament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the eminent Popiſh Families in <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Brown,</hi> and <hi>Plunket</hi> have often (with oftentation) acknowledged, beſides the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Negotiation of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Brent,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſt and expert ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager of ſuch a buſineſs) to manie of the active Papiſts of <hi>England</hi> at the ſame time, doth fully manifeſt the ſame with ſuits, with the conſtant expreſſions of the Rebels, in all parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> affirming there could bee no exſpectation of anie conſiderable, or ſeaſonable relief out of <hi>England.</hi> It is alſo too well known, that when the Cavalier intereſt had life in it, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Romaniſts would often boaſt of this their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece their managing the <hi>Iriſh</hi> inſurrection (as they termed it) at that ſeaſon wherein it ſhould finde leaſt oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>England,</hi> and ſo moſt ſucceſsful for the improvement of the Catholick cauſ.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99021:21"/>
                     <head>The names of the old Engliſh, now ſtated and planted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as can at preſent bee remembred of many hundreds there reſident, at the beginning of this Rebellion, and for the moſt part yet being there, with the mention what Noble men are of thoſe Families, without mentioning what greater and further Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are of each, or any of their Names or Families, are as follloweth.</head>
                     <item>Archbalds</item>
                     <item>Aſhes, <hi>aliàs</hi> de fraxineto</item>
                     <item>Almers</item>
                     <item>Allens</item>
                     <item>Arthurs</item>
                     <item>Archers</item>
                     <item>Ailworth or Ailward</item>
                     <item>Audleys</item>
                     <item>Archdecons</item>
                     <item>Arundels</item>
                     <item>Butlers<note place="margin">6 Noble men of the name.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bourks<note place="margin">5 Noble men.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Barries<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Breminghams<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Barnwels<note place="margin">2 Noblemen.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Brownes.</item>
                     <item>Bagnals</item>
                     <item>Burnels</item>
                     <item>Baathes</item>
                     <item>Bellow <hi>alias</hi> Bedlows</item>
                     <item>Blakes</item>
                     <item>Belins</item>
                     <item>Bagots</item>
                     <item>Blackneys</item>
                     <item>Brandons</item>
                     <item>Blanchfeilds</item>
                     <item>Benſons</item>
                     <item>Balfe</item>
                     <item>Boiſe</item>
                     <item>Brewer</item>
                     <item>Bale</item>
                     <item>Brian</item>
                     <item>Buſher</item>
                     <item>Burford</item>
                     <item>Brereton</item>
                     <item>Barret</item>
                     <item>Benfeild</item>
                     <item>Baron</item>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99021:22"/>
                     <item>Birt <hi>alias</hi> Britt</item>
                     <item>Barington</item>
                     <item>Baſgravile</item>
                     <item>Beard</item>
                     <item>Courcies<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cheevers</item>
                     <item>Cuſacks</item>
                     <item>Cogan</item>
                     <item>Cadels</item>
                     <item>Colleys</item>
                     <item>Cosby</item>
                     <item>Cods</item>
                     <item>Cruces</item>
                     <item>Chamberlain,</item>
                     <item>Chaceys <hi>or</hi> Caſeys</item>
                     <item>Clintons</item>
                     <item>Clinches</item>
                     <item>Comerfords</item>
                     <item>Coſgraves</item>
                     <item>Colbies</item>
                     <item>Coſbies</item>
                     <item>Condon</item>
                     <item>Coſſen</item>
                     <item>Conron</item>
                     <item>Caſhell</item>
                     <item>Cardiff</item>
                     <item>Colclogh</item>
                     <item>Crolie</item>
                     <item>Carey</item>
                     <item>Coffie</item>
                     <item>Coppinger</item>
                     <item>Comins</item>
                     <item>Clundake</item>
                     <item>Dillons<note place="margin">2 Noble men.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Dowdales</item>
                     <item>Dungans</item>
                     <item>Darcies</item>
                     <item>Devereuxes</item>
                     <item>Daltons, Drilands</item>
                     <item>Dormers</item>
                     <item>Donnels <hi>or M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
                        </hi>-Donnels<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Downes</item>
                     <item>Denn, Dixon</item>
                     <item>Dromgool</item>
                     <item>Daniel</item>
                     <item>Dobbin</item>
                     <item>Deering</item>
                     <item>Delamares</item>
                     <item>Deece</item>
                     <item>Davels</item>
                     <item>Draicot</item>
                     <item>Dardes</item>
                     <item>Drakes</item>
                     <item>Dexeters</item>
                     <item>Elliots</item>
                     <item>Evers <hi>alias</hi> Ewre</item>
                     <item>Euſtacks</item>
                     <item>Eſmond</item>
                     <item>Everard, <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fitz-Garalds<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fitz-Morris,<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99021:22"/>
                     <item>Fitz-VVilliams<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fitz-Simons</item>
                     <item>Fitz-Harries</item>
                     <item>Frends, Fians</item>
                     <item>Fennels</item>
                     <item>Fitz Stephens</item>
                     <item>French</item>
                     <item>Font <hi>or</hi> Fawnt</item>
                     <item>Fitz Zery</item>
                     <item>Fitz-Leones</item>
                     <item>Flemings<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Flatsburie</item>
                     <item>Foxes</item>
                     <item>Foreſtal</item>
                     <item>Forlongs</item>
                     <item>Fitz Nichols</item>
                     <item>Forſters</item>
                     <item>Finglaſſes</item>
                     <item>Fottrels</item>
                     <item>Fanings</item>
                     <item>Faies</item>
                     <item>Frenches</item>
                     <item>Garnons</item>
                     <item>Grants</item>
                     <item>Garvies</item>
                     <item>Grahams</item>
                     <item>Gerons</item>
                     <item>Graces</item>
                     <item>Goldings</item>
                     <item>Goghes</item>
                     <item>Galtrims</item>
                     <item>Galwaies</item>
                     <item>Hores</item>
                     <item>Harpenies</item>
                     <item>Huſſies</item>
                     <item>Haſſans</item>
                     <item>Hides <hi>or</hi> de la Hides</item>
                     <item>Hardins</item>
                     <item>Holliwoods</item>
                     <item>Hetheringtons</item>
                     <item>Howlins</item>
                     <item>Harpools</item>
                     <item>Handcock</item>
                     <item>Hays</item>
                     <item>Hadſors</item>
                     <item>Hurleys, Hopps</item>
                     <item>Harries, Harriſons</item>
                     <item>Herberts, Horis</item>
                     <item>Harold.</item>
                     <item>Jordans</item>
                     <item>Jans</item>
                     <item>Joices</item>
                     <item>Jacobs</item>
                     <item>Itchingham</item>
                     <item>Kings</item>
                     <item>Keatings</item>
                     <item>Kents</item>
                     <item>Laulis, Lenard</item>
                     <item>Luttrels, Lanfant</item>
                     <item>Lacies</item>
                     <item>Lanes</item>
                     <item>Linches</item>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99021:23"/>
                     <item>Lovels</item>
                     <item>Leiceſters</item>
                     <item>Ledwiches</item>
                     <item>Longs</item>
                     <item>Locks</item>
                     <item>Lamports</item>
                     <item>Moores</item>
                     <item>Miſſets</item>
                     <item>Maſterſons</item>
                     <item>Morris</item>
                     <item>Martins</item>
                     <item>Mandevils</item>
                     <item>Meilers</item>
                     <item>Moilers</item>
                     <item>Malpas</item>
                     <item>Maſons</item>
                     <item>Mellins</item>
                     <item>Netervils<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nugents<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nangles</item>
                     <item>Nottinghams</item>
                     <item>Nevils</item>
                     <item>Ovingtons</item>
                     <item>Plunkets<note place="margin">3 Noble men.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Preſtons<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Powers<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Purcels</item>
                     <item>Peirce</item>
                     <item>Pigot</item>
                     <item>Pendergafts</item>
                     <item>Philips</item>
                     <item>Peppards</item>
                     <item>Penteins</item>
                     <item>Petits</item>
                     <item>Prowdfoots</item>
                     <item>Roches<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Rogers</item>
                     <item>Rices</item>
                     <item>Reinolds</item>
                     <item>Rochforths</item>
                     <item>Roceter</item>
                     <item>Ruſſels</item>
                     <item>Rooths</item>
                     <item>Remond</item>
                     <item>Reinolds</item>
                     <item>Stantons</item>
                     <item>Sentlawrences<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sarsfields<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Skelton</item>
                     <item>Strong</item>
                     <item>Sedgraves</item>
                     <item>Sinnots</item>
                     <item>Shortels</item>
                     <item>Sempes</item>
                     <item>Sankies</item>
                     <item>Sigen</item>
                     <item>Samonds <hi>aliàs</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Amonds</item>
                     <item>Scurlock</item>
                     <item>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> John</item>
                     <item>Sherlock</item>
                     <item>Stanleys</item>
                     <item>Stapletons</item>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99021:23"/>
                     <item>Soars</item>
                     <item>Stephens</item>
                     <item>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Michael</item>
                     <item>Silveſter</item>
                     <item>Suttons</item>
                     <item>Stritch</item>
                     <item>Staffords</item>
                     <item>Swords</item>
                     <item>Scallann</item>
                     <item>Skiddies <hi>aliàs</hi> Scudamore</item>
                     <item>Sermons</item>
                     <item>Smiths</item>
                     <item>Sentlegers</item>
                     <item>Savages</item>
                     <item>Talbots</item>
                     <item>Tints</item>
                     <item>Taffs<note place="margin">1 Noble man.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>Turnors</item>
                     <item>Tirrels</item>
                     <item>Trawnt</item>
                     <item>Travers</item>
                     <item>Tallon</item>
                     <item>Uſhers</item>
                     <item>Verdons</item>
                     <item>Verden</item>
                     <item>Veal</item>
                     <item>Walſhes</item>
                     <item>Wolverſtons</item>
                     <item>Wogans</item>
                     <item>Wottons</item>
                     <item>Whits</item>
                     <item>Waddings</item>
                     <item>Walters</item>
                     <item>Wiſes</item>
                     <item>Weſtons</item>
                     <item>Welleſley</item>
                     <item>Workley</item>
                     <item>Whitties</item>
                     <item>Wickens</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>THere are 29 Families more, not there named of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcent, which have every one a Noble man thereof, whoſe Eſtates are in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And there are but eight noble men in <hi>Ireland</hi> of meer <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that the Nobilitie of Engliſh deſcent (not recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe that live in <hi>England,</hi> who onely have honors and no eſtates there) are ſeven to one of the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And there are in all about ninetie two Nobilitie of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99021:24"/>
                  <p>I had almoſt forgotten one thing of conſiderable value, which is this, admitting that the pretended antient title of the meer <hi>Iriſh</hi> were (as it is not) good to the Lands of <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet nothing is more true then that great parts thereof have been bought at dear rates, by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and more would have been, had the <hi>Iriſh</hi> frequent proffers a little before their laſt Rebellion been accepted of by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to whom the <hi>Queriſt</hi> muſt need's allow a cleer intereſt in the Lands ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed; as alſo to their perſonal eſtates, and thoſe that deprive them of ſuch their Civil Right, can bee no other then thievs and robbers, and at once root out God's Law, man's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, and National Equitie, ſo juſt is this <hi>Queriſt</hi> to God and Nature, on whom hee would father the <hi>Iriſh</hi> depredations and murthers; And this may in ſom meaſure ſuffice for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the firſt <hi>Quere,</hi> at leaſt to ſhew how the <hi>Queriſt</hi> ſeek's to blinde inadvertent men with a far fetched ſuppoſition, which want's ſubſtance in everie particular (when examined) yet framed as an Engine to retard all ſuccors for <hi>Ireland,</hi> then at the point to bee loſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The ſecond Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVHether a people or Nation ſo ſetled, have not a power to establiſh all Laws, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Offices, and Officers amongſt themſelvs, and to oppoſe and execute all ſuch as ſhall endeavor, to impoſe and obtrude upon them, Laws, Government, Offices and Officers, without, or againſt their conſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99021:24"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Iriſh</hi> are not ſuch a people or Nation, ſo ſetled, have not a power to eſtabliſh all Laws, Government, &amp;c. But the people of <hi>England,</hi> to whom <hi>Ireland</hi> belong's, are, and have ſuch a power to eſtabliſh all Laws, Government, Offices and Officers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> their own Dominions, and to oppoſe and execute all ſuch, as ſhall endeavor to impoſe and obtrude in their ſaid Dominions, Laws, Government, Offices, and Officers, without, or againſt their conſent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The third Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether God and Nature having given a people and Nation ſuch a poſſeſsion of Lands, and ſom other Prince or people ſhould invade or conquer them, deprive them of much of their Land, impoſe Laws, Government, and Officers upon them, without, or againſt their conſent; if it bee anie other then robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the Invaders and the juſt right of the invaded and conquered, to cut off their enemies, to procure their own Freedom and inheritance again?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The third Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>GOd and Nature hath ſo given <hi>Ireland</hi> for a poſſeſſion and Government to the Inhabitants, and people of <hi>England,</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99021:25"/>from the beginning, as in the Anſwer to the firſt <hi>Quere</hi> is cleer. And this <hi>Quere</hi> more properly relate's to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> juſt title againſt the claim of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who were not the original In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiters of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſo no claim from God and Nature for ſuch a poſſeſſion of theirs; and therefore the <hi>Iriſh</hi> invaſion and expulſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> depriving them of much of their Lands; framing Laws, Government, and Officers in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Dominions, or againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſent, is no other then robberie in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Invaders, and it is the juſt right of the Invaded (and part conquered) <hi>Engliſh</hi> to cut off their <hi>Iriſh</hi> enemies, and to procure theirs and their Brethren's free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to regain their own lawful government and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
                  <p>And for further reſolution, this <hi>Quere,</hi> as it is ſtated, is not the caſe of the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> For as before is truly ſaid, the permiſſion of the Britiſh planted, and gave them firſt footing there, and the ſeveral Conqueſts (or rather reducements of them) by the Britiſh there, was no invaſion, but a bringing of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling <hi>Iriſh</hi> to due obedience, and Chriſtian-like ſubmiſſion to their ſupreme Governors, whoſe right onely it is, to impoſe Laws, Governors, and Officers upon them, and therefore no robberie for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to enter on their own Land, but moſt juſt to puniſh, and diſſeiſ them, who by their frequent Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions were no more to bee truſted with them, then a mad-man with a ſword: yet the indulgence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government hath alway as been ſo great, as to take but a part of the Rebel's eſtates, whereas they had forfeited all by their iterated former rebellions; Then where is the cauſ or right of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to cut off the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in cold blood, in time of peace, and in the beſt Government, and improvement the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ever injoyed?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99021:25"/>
                  <head>The fourth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether length of time, where the original Nation is diſtinct from the Conqueror, doth ſwallow up the right of the conquered, that they have no right to ſeek after, and regain their own freedoms and poſſeſsions, yea or no?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The fourth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>LEngth of time cannot privilege, or diſcharge a people ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally ſubordinate to another, from their due conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and obedience to the Laws and Government of thoſe, by whoſe permiſſion they were received into the Verge of their dominions, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were into the dominions of the Britiſh in <hi>Ireland,</hi> neither are the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels (as now compoſed) a diſtinct Nation of themſelvs, nor ſo diſtinct in deſcent from thoſe, who at all times lawfully reduced them. But that the now moſt ruling, and powerful partie of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels are deſcended of <hi>Engliſh</hi> lineage, as aforeſaid; and neither they, nor the other old degenerate <hi>Engliſh</hi> can juſtly pretend to anie Land there, but what hath been paſſed unto them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great Seal of that Land, and therefore their freedom and right cannot bee anie wiſe ſaid to bee ſwallowed up by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for, from anie other they cannot truly derive either their Freedom, Lands or poſſeſſions, as beeing granted unto them by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the meer <hi>Iriſh</hi> (as is aboveſaid) not beeing half of the Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor of anie conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable riches, ſtrength or policie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99021:26"/>
                  <head>The fift Quere.</head>
                  <p>HOw can the conquered juſtly bee called, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Rebels, if anie time, they ſhall ſeek and endeavor to free themſelvs, and to regain their own Lands and Liberties?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The fift Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> now in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt the power and juſt right of <hi>England,</hi> are no better then perfidious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, intruders, and inhumane blood-ſuckers, not onely for the cauſes before ſhewed, but for their iterated Rebellions, and former maſſacring of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and have been well known to bee ſuch brutiſh enemies for divers ages paſt; And if it ſhould bee allowed, that they at their wills and pleaſures might ſhake off the yoke of obedience, and to perpetrate the inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane cruelties, ſemblable to their former, then would they at length (as it were) change their ſhape of men into the ſtate of Divels.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The ſixt Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether <hi>Julius Caeſar, Alexander</hi> the great, <hi>William</hi> Duke of Normandie, or anie other the great Conquerors of the world, were anie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99021:26"/>other then ſo manie great and lawleſs thievs; And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee not altogether as unjust to take our neighbor Nations, Lands, and liberties from them, as our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor's goods of our own Nation?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The ſixt Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>HEre might I now ſuſpend further labor (as ſuperfluous, in conteſting with extravagant impertinencies, having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended much time upon the main. But I have alreadie (as I conceiv) irrecoverably thrown down the falſ foundation, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which this preſumptuous Impoſtor doth rear the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of his inſnaring Queres. In the fall whereof they are ſlaughtered, as I may ſaie, in the mother's bellie, reſolved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well objected, and may bee left as dead, and buried in their firſt ruines, yet ſince the eaſieſt part of my task is now behinde, I will wave the trouble I might juſtly avoid in beeing filent, and crave leav to proceed in the ſolution of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interrogations to their utmoſt borders, leſt by ſuch ſilence I ſhould give advantage to the contriver of them, to ſurfet with conceit of his ſuppoſed unanſwerable ſuggeſtions.</p>
                  <p>By this queſtion that now look's ſo big, ſtare's us in the face, and ſpeak's ſo loud; the <hi>Queriſt</hi> may drive ſom of mean Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into amazement, though indeed hee manifeſteth but a weakneſs in that his endeavor, to render the <hi>Engliſh</hi> title du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious, and make our Nation, perſons, and intereſt, odious by an infamous indicting of us under the notion of thievs, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, invaders, &amp;c. Onely for our credit thus much, hee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign's with us, or us with them, the great Conquerors of the world, <hi>Julius Caeſar, Alexander the great,</hi> and <hi>William the Norman,</hi> in whom (indeed) all the great Rulers of the earth are concerned and comprehended by this pernitious ſtickler for <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels; of whoſe ridiculous follie beeing ſenfible enough, I give him no other Anſwer then a flat and expreſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99021:27"/>denial to that hee aim's to gain by a confeſſion on our part, and what hee is not able to prove on his own; But I laie hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which (undeſired) hee grant's unto us in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and then to anſwer the <hi>Quere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Taking him therefore upon his own confeſſion, hee who elſ-where ſtrongly endeavor's to ſmother our original proprietie, and intereſt, doth there beſlow upon us a four-fold good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle (if other things ſhould fail) to that Land, unto which they the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſo unjuſtly pretend; As in his ſeveral <hi>Queres,</hi> firſt a conqueſt; Secondly, a preſcription, and actual poſſeſſion in the Britiſh; Thirdly, a Legiſlative power; fourthly their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, (though a diſtinct people, yet living amongſt us) unto the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government.</p>
                  <p>The Anſwer now followeth, which is reduced to theſe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative poſitions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the Conquerors therein mentioned, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, ought not to carrie the character of lawleſs thievs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that titles and dominions atchieved by conqueſt, are not robberies, but juſtifiable titles and poſſeſſions.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of theſe concern's the perſon of the Conqueror, the ſecond the right of the things poſſeſſed. Might wee but propound one <hi>Quere</hi> to this bold Aſſertor, it ſhould bee this.</p>
                  <p>What Autor can hee produce for this prophane and abſurd Language? the worſt of prophane hiſtories afford no pattern to theſe expreſſions.</p>
                  <p>Is a Conqueror no more then a <hi>Bandetto,</hi> a Pirate, a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas, or one of the Arabian fraternities? Muſt the actions of publick perſons impowred by God, acted by divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſions, and oftentimes executing for God an unknown Commiſſion againſt the Inhabitants of the world for their tranſgreſſions, bee ſtained with, and carrie the black Character of <hi>Lawleſs thievs;</hi> Surely no, this is not the language of the ſervant of the living God, but of the ſervant of the lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the falſ accuſer.</p>
                  <p>What if the actions of theſe Conquerors bee chargeable with ſom irregularities, and perſonal vitioſities uſually concurrent
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99021:27"/>in victories. They may bee matters of lamentation to the world, and ſad accounts too; but no ground for ſuch deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To instance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us pitch upon <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> that Babylonian Monarch, called <hi>The hammer of the whole earth, the great deſtroier of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.23.</note> was hee not one of the worſt of Adverſaries unto the people of God, witneſs Sion's complaint againſt him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.34; 35.</note> yet was ever this infamous title attributed to him by anie of the captivated people.</p>
                  <p>Nay, doth not God ſpeak of him in tearms of honor, looking on him as an inſtrument to act his own deſign, beeing one of the rods of his anger, and the ſtaff of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtyling him oftentimes <hi>My ſervant,</hi> and his work <hi>his ſervice,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29.18, 19, 20. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.</note> and one unto whom God for his own work aſſigned <hi>Egypt</hi> for the wages of his Armie; And doth not <hi>Daniel</hi> the ſervant of the living God, and a Captive of the blood Roial, honor him with the awful tearms and title of Magiſtracie in theſe words; <hi>O King, live for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſhall wee ſaie of <hi>Ceſar Octavius,</hi> under whoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment the Saviour of the world was born, by whoſe power the Jewiſh Nation were kept in ſubjection, doth not the Evangeliſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Luke</hi> put that Romane ſtamp of dignitie <hi>(Auguſtus)</hi> upon him: <hi>Nomen quaſi Sanctum &amp; veneratione dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> ſaith <hi>Burgenſis,</hi> The Jews gave him the title of a lawful Magiſtrate, and a King, ſaying, wee have no King, but <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. Auguſtine</hi> had reverend language towards the Ceſarian Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, affirming this, <hi>Autores belli Dei miniſtri;</hi> and in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Boniface</hi> a militarie Commander in the Romane Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſeth theſe words: <hi>Nequaquam putare debes eos qui rei-publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae inſerviunt, Deo placere non poſſe: John</hi> the Baptiſt (who loſt his head for the freedom of his Language) when the Ceſarian ſouldiers of the meaner rank frequented his Miniſtrie, did not bid them laie down their Arms as unlawful, or frown upon them as thievs, or diſcourage them with ſuch Dialects, but diſcipline's them as Scholars for the School of Chriſt. <hi>Do violence to no man, and bee content with your wages.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John.</note> If God from the mouth of the holie ſon, ſtyle's them <hi>ſervants;</hi> If holie
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99021:28"/>men taught by the Spirit of God, and religious knowing men never took up ſuch vilifying Language againſt the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors of the world, and the <hi>hammers of the earth</hi> the <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the Perſians, the Grecians, and the Romans</hi> to whom the ſupreme Lord of all gave the Kingdoms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the earth; how unwarrantable will it bee for the ſons of men to open their mouths contumeliouſly againſt the Miniſters of the Lord of Hoſts, into whoſe hands hee hath put the revenging ſword, and crowned it with victorie, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declaring the ſecret purpoſes of his good pleaſure, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe people againſt whom they are ſent, and preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for Juſtice and Judgment.</p>
                  <p>Having thus ſetled the unqueſtionable title of honored Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie upon ſuch Conquerors, and vindicated them from the black infamie (the Language of hell, and not of Saints) which the <hi>Queriſt</hi> would intail upon them, I now com to make good my ſecond Poſition, in anſwer to this ſixt <hi>Quere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A title or dominion atteined by Conqueſt is not robberie, as the Conquerors are not lawleſs thievs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.39. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.10. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.25.</note> God putting all their acquirements by Conqueſts upon the accompt of his own free donation, and not upon robberie or theft.</p>
                  <p>Take a ſhort view of mutations in the world made by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in former ages: May not the ſame bee affirmed from thence, and other paralel Scriptures, that the mutations and revolutions of Crowns and Kingdoms, Governments and Governors, the breaking in and caſting out of Nations, are the effect of divine ordination, managed and brought to paſs by exorbitant and irregular motions of men, publickly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred, and by extraordinarie provocations raiſed up to the attempting of actions, above the rank and ſphere of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie diſpenſations.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17.</note> Is not the power of God ſtill the ſame, <hi>to give his kingdoms of the earth, when, and to whom hee pleaſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was the Judgment of <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> writing de <hi>Jure belli, Non tantùm à principio mutationes factas eſſe, ſed in poſterioribus, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore belli; Later ages will produce Mutations in times of war, aſwel as former.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then why may not befal to thoſe Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland</hi> (which challenge the Land to bee given them by God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99021:28"/>and Nature) that which hath betided other Nations, by the ſecret counſels of that God, in whoſe hands the Inhabitants of the earth are toſſed as a ball?</p>
                  <p>Did not <hi>Eneas</hi> by conqueſt of the <hi>Latines</hi> ſettle his poſteritie in <hi>Italie?</hi> did not the <hi>Franks,</hi> by invaſion and conqueſts take poſſeſſion of <hi>Gallia</hi> (now their native habitation)? was not <hi>Britain</hi> in <hi>France</hi> ſurprized by the power of the <hi>Engliſh Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and from them denominated, continuing in their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion to this daie? Did not the <hi>Huns</hi> becom Maſters of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonia</hi> (now of them called <hi>Hungarie;</hi>) And to conclude, is not Conqueſt an univerſal title throughout the world? Is not that <hi>Jus gentium quod ubique valet;</hi> And if this <hi>Jus Belli</hi> ſtand for a Plea for them, why may not wee then ſaie as the Civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians fully reſoly the lawfulneſs and proprietie of things got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by war in this known <hi>Maxime, Ea quae ab hoſtibus capiuntur, jure gentium ſtatim fiunt capientium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot omit ſom material inſtances, and ſo conclude the Anſwer to this <hi>Quere,</hi> whereby the preſent acting power of a Conqueror is allowed, and approved in an uſurper by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was born under an uſurping power to teach us, as a judicious Commentator obſerv's, <hi>Indicat deinde ipsâ nativitate ſe non pellere magiſtratum ordinarium adventu ſuo, imò approbare,</hi> who, beſides his univerſal title to all the world, had an indubitable title and claim to the temporal Kingdom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> then under the Romane uſurping power, (Witneſs that antient Manuſcript, <hi>Michael Nauclerus de Monarchia divina, ex libro vaticano</hi>) yet did ſo far ſubmit unto the title of Conqueſt, and his intruſion, that hee the lawful heir was contented to becom a Subject in his own Land, <hi>Eodem tempore quo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ti Tyranni occupabant;</hi> though <hi>all power was his, and hee that little ſtone</hi> foretold <hi>that hee ſhould bee cut out of the Mountain, &amp;c.</hi> yet hee neither ſmite's them with tongue,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45.</note> nor oppoſeth them by practice, but practically uſeth and teacheth obedience by paying tribute, yea, becom's an Advocate for <hi>Ceſar's</hi> intereſt; <hi>Give unto Ceſar that which is Ceſar's,</hi> and in a word was ſo far from exclaiming againſt that Romane (though uſurping) autoritie, that hee <hi>looking up to Heaven, affirm's the invader's powers to bee of God,</hi> and therefore afterwards ſubmit's
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99021:29"/>to an unjuſt Sentence of death, whoſe ſteps, the holie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle following, and filled with the Spirit of the ſame Chriſt, the onely bleſſed potentate doth in expreſs terms, without excluſion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. v. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> enjoin ſubmiſſion to all ſorts of powers, &amp;c. Hee ſaie's not, <hi>they have no title, they came in by Conqueſt, they are thievs, Robbers,</hi> but honor's them with the title of lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and command's the conquered Subject upon pain of damnation, to afford obedience unto them as the Miniſters of God, uſing theſe words, that <hi>all powers that bee, are of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for the later part of this <hi>Quere, viz Whether it bee not altogether as unjuſt to take our neighbor's Lands and Liberties from them, as our neighbor's goods from our own Nation?</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is anſwered, that although the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have verie long uſurped the poſſeſſion of the Lands and Liberties of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> (beeing the Lands and Liberties in the neighboring Countrie, which the <hi>Queriſt</hi> meaneth, and which of right, and from antiquitie, and ſo until this daie do truly and juſtly belong to the <hi>Engliiſh,</hi> as in the firſt <hi>Quere</hi> is reſolved:) Yet neither when this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Rebellion brake out in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor of a number of yeers before, were anie Lands or Liberties unjuſtly taken, held, or deteined from anie the Rebels of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And hee can pretend to nothing but dull ignorance, that know's it not to have been ſtill conſiſtent, with the Laws and Cuſtoms aſwel of <hi>England,</hi> as of other civil Nations of the world, to ſeiz, and take the goods and liberties of ſuch neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of their own Nation, as would not ſtoop to obedience, but Rebel againſt the known Laws of anie Land where they lived, eſpecially, wilful Law-breakers, ſuch as ſhould firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and attempt depredations, and ſurpriſing of the goods and eſtates of the obedient parties; the like Laws beeing for ſuch contemners and Rebels alſo, in ſuch caſes to loſe their lives.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99021:29"/>
                  <head>The ſeventh Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether God at the laſt daie will not call men to an account, even for thoſe things which they are unaccountable for here, as great Conquerors are?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The ſeventh Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>GOd at the laſt daie will juſtifie all men, that zealouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the work of his own righteous juſtice, and that are inſtrumental in the propagation of his truth and glorie, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> now are, and as (I am confident) they will perſiſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> (their own Countrie) againſt, and upon the wicked Inhabitants thereof, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, who for their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as I may boldly ſaie, ſtink in the noſtrils of the Lord, and of all his ſervants, and muſt at laſt (without doubt) bee brought to an account for all their ungrateful, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, bloodie and barbarous actions, wherein the hand of the Lord is moſt viſible unto us, having alreadie brought manie to the ſword, deſtroied ſom by famine, but far more by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and other waies of his Juſtice, and now thoſe, whoſe perſons as yet met not with thoſe Judgments, and proudly triumphed over, and ſtood upon the necks of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable,<note place="margin">This at large ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear's by the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> upon oath.</note> and infinitely diſtreſſed <hi>Engliſh,</hi> do like duſt before the winde flie from the faces of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, not daring to juſtifie the leaſt of their acts or underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, but for refuge flie to Mountains, woods, bogs, and other obſcure and unacceſſible places, <hi>curſing now the firſt plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, contrivers, and beginners of their Rebellion, and helliſh deſigns.</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99021:30"/>And doth not the <hi>Queriſt</hi> think that manie of theſe bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckers in this world, and the reſt in the world to com ſhall meet with condign puniſhment ſuitable to their demerits?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The eighth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether the condition of the conquered bee not <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the condition of the Conquerors bee not <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> unjuſtly tearmed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and their cauſ juſt, and <hi>England</hi> a thieving uſurping Tyrannie, and their cauſ altogether unjust, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against God and Nature, and therein, ſuch as no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious conſcientious man can aſsist, or bid God speed?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The eighth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe condition of the conquered is not <hi>Ireland,</hi> beeing (as aforeſaid) not a diſtinct nation and people, but the greateſt part of them conſiſting of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or thoſe from thence extracted: And the ſeveral Conqueſts of them, but reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to legal and civil obedience, to the juſt and proper right and intereſt of <hi>England.</hi> Nor can the condition of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors of them bee, as over an abſolute Nation: therefore the Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> now in arms againſt the juſt rights and proprietie of <hi>England,</hi> are properly and palpably Rebels, and their cauſ unjuſt, and <hi>England's</hi> a legal power, right and Government, and their cauſ altogether juſt, beeing for God and Nature; For God, to puniſh the rebellious, wicked, and obſtinate, to root out Idolatrie, to plant and dreſs the Lord's
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99021:30"/>Vineyard, by holding out the glorious light of the truth, and not ſuffer it to bee covered or trampled on: For <hi>Nature,</hi> ſuch as all judicious, conſcientious men will aſſiſt, and bid God ſpeed unto, beeing to redeem their brethren, the diſpoiled Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> reſtore them to their juſt and lawful poſſeſſions, vindicate the robberies, murthers, tortures, rapes, and inhumane cruelties, barbarouſly executed on them, and reduce that Countrie to Peace and quietneſs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The ninth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether it bee not the dutie of everie honest man, by all fair and peaceable means, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor the diverting of the States, from the proſecution of ſo unjuſt a cauſ, eſpecially, decline all means where him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf might promote the ſame: but to ſhew his utter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of it?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The ninth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IT is the dutie of everie honeſt man, by all earneſt, zealous, and lawful means, to endeavor the encouragement and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the State of <hi>England,</hi> for their proſecution of their ſo juſt a cauſ, eſpecially to undertake all means, and to run through all difficulties, whereby hee himſelf might promote the ſame, and ſhew his willingneſs unto, and good liking of it, and hee neither is, nor can bee a good Chriſtian, that will not contribute to the ſuppreſſion of theſe Idolaters, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and apparent enemies of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99021:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>The tenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVHether thoſe that conted for their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> now) ſhall not make themſelvs altogether unexcuſable, if they ſhall intrench upon other's freedoms: And whether it bee not an especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al note, and characterizing badg of a true pattern of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to indeavor the juſt freedom of all men, as well as his own?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The tenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that contend for their freedom (as the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>agliſh</hi> now) who are backt and ſeconded by original juſt Principles, fundamental Laws, inherent Rights, legal and due grants, and acknowledgment of their rights from their former accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Governors, make's the reſolution flatly oppoſite unto, and inconſiſtent with the rebellious Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland;</hi> who have neither original Principles, fundamental Laws, inherent Rights, legal and due grants, and acknowledgments of their rights, from their former rightful Governors, in anie ſort or manner, diſtinct and ſeparate from the right, power, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>England</hi> over them; But as a member to the bodie, ſo is <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>England;</hi> And therefore <hi>England</hi> need's no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, but is everie waie juſtifiable to rectifie, or cut off a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, rebellious and gangren'd member, who never had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on it, or reteined anie other defect, reſtriction, or freedom then the whole bodie ſuffered. And if the indeavors of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99021:31"/>have been ſo candid, as to make <hi>Ireland</hi> a fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of its own freedom, and enjoyment of Laws and Libertie, equal with it ſelf, in ſuch of the Inhabitants as are capable and deſerving the ſame, it is a ſpecial note and characterizing badg of a true Pattern of freedom, to bring ſuch as belong to them into the like condition of themſelvs, and to ſuppreſs thoſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> aſwel as thoſe in <hi>England</hi> that oppoſe the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The Eleventh Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVHether in Judgment and Conſcience the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are not to bee juſtified, in all that they have don against the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in complying with, aſsiſting, and ſeeking aſsiſtance from anie that would, or will bee <hi>England's</hi> enemies, to preſerv, and deliver them from the crueltie and uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> rather then to becom ſlaves to their wills; And whether the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would not do as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> do, were they in like condition?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The eleventh Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IF Traitors, murtherers, raviſhers, robbers, cruel inhumane perſecutors of true Chriſtians, ſacrilegious, abominable Idolaters are juſtifiable, then are the Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> now in arms againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to bee juſtified; But if by the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99021:32"/>Law of God and man, ſuch of their partakers, Abettors, and countenancers are to bee proſecuted and puniſhed by thoſe, into whoſe hands God hath put the ſword of legal power, and juſt Government, as now in the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Then in Judgment and conſcience, the ſaid Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland</hi> deſerv ſharp proſecution and juſt condemnation, and the rather, for that they (to uphold themſelvs in their miſchief) have againſt their dutie and Ioialtie to the lawful Government and right of <hi>England</hi> aſſiſted, and ſought aſſiſtance from ſuch as are, and alwaies have been <hi>England's</hi> profeſſed enemies, and therefore, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to endeavor the acquifition of their own juſt rights, and to puniſh thoſe rebellious, obſtinate, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> is but their dutie, and ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, not crueltie, equitie and juſt right; not uſurpation. They deſerving the greateſt ſeveritie for their falſhood and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, who ſo exorbitantly abuſed the greateſt freedom that ever anie Nation enjoied, and were not made ſlaves to the will of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, but for manie years paſt, had as much freedom (and far more) then their evil manners ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them capable of.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The twelfth Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVHether the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would account anie thing crueltie enough for them, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe upon the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould diſpoſſeſs them in <hi>England,</hi> and tyrannize over them here, as the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> have don over them there, if afterwards the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> ſhould get the upper hand?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99021:32"/>
                  <head>The twelfth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Engliſh</hi> never diſpoſſed nor tyrannized over the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> either in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> but contrariwiſe were ever indulgent and loving to them; and now as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will account nothing ſevere enough (if warrantable by God's Law) for them to execute upon the rebellious <hi>Iriſh,</hi> if they ſhould diſpoſſeſs the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and tyrannize over them here, as they, the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> have moſt unlawfully don over <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland:</hi> So it is warrantable by God's Law to recover their right in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by the ſame Law (if they get the upper hand) ſeverely to proſecute and puniſh the blood-guiltie Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> it beeing a dutie and truſt impoſed on them by God, againſt ſuch Idolaters and murtherers, and none ought, (without great offence) but proſecute ſuch a cauſe with effect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The thirteenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether it bee not the dutie of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, rather to repent of the oppreſsion, uſurpation and intruſion of themſelvs, their Kings and forefathers, then with a high hand to purſue thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of violence?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The thirteenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IT is the part and dutie of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation rather to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and force the rebellious member <hi>Ireland</hi> to repent their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99021:33"/>oppreſſion, uſurpation and intruſion into the right and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and for their violent depriving them and their harmleſs neighbors of their Liberties, lives, goods, Lands, and other Eſtates, and for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to recover their own rights, (in all ages made good by the expence of their fore-father's blood and treaſure) and with a high hand to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the deſigns of the oppoſers; and where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> never oppreſſed, uſurped, or intruded upon the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> there they need no repentance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The fourteenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether (if they ſhall ſtill purſue the ſame) it will not maintain a laſting chargeable war, to bee a large and ſtrange footing for the enemies to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's</hi> peace to ſtand upon, to render the Nation to bee no true lovers of freedom, but of domination, give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the enemies to blaſpheme, make our Religion odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by perpetual piracie even utterly ſpoil all our trade by Sea, and ſo bee at the laſt our own ruine, and whether the gain at the laſt by a perfect conqueſt over them (which is uncertain) will equipoiz all that charge and blood, that muſt bee ſpilt for the obteining of the ſame, eſpecially conſidering their eternal loſs, dying in the proſecution of ſo unjuſt a cauſ?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99021:33"/>
                  <head>The fourteenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IF they, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> now in the nick of time purſue the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, conſidering the preſent power and poſture that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is in, and the great number of its able bodies fit for emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which on a ſetled peace at home cannot bee better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied or beſtowed, then in ſo conſcionable a ſervice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the honor and glorie of God, the peace and quiet of all the Dominions of <hi>England,</hi> the advance of Trade, the terror of <hi>England's</hi> enemies, the gaining of a moſt fruitful and plentiful receptacle for a flowing off-ſpring, (if now ſo enabled) they ſhall effectually purſue the ſervice againſt the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (beeing ſo diſſeminated and ſcattered as they now are) it will not maintein a laſting chargeable war. For now but a competent number to bee ſent out of <hi>England,</hi> with thoſe faithful and noble ones, their Commilitants now there will (doubtleſs) by God's gracious aſſiſtance, do the bleſſed work of reducing them, and remove the largeſt and ſtrongeſt footings the enemies of <hi>England</hi> have gotten, render the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>England</hi> to bee true Lovers of Freedom, and the noble preſervers of that part of their bodie and dominion; This al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will take away all occaſion from the enemie to blaſpheme, ſince the true worſhip and ſervice of God will bee advanced in place of idolatrous Popetie, (ſo much of late years hazarding the peace of <hi>England</hi>) make our Religion (that true one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) beautiful, lovely, and delightful; free our Seas from the brood of <hi>Dunkirkers, Pickaro's,</hi> and others of the like ſtamp (<hi>Iriſh</hi> Pirats) when they ſhall have no place of harbor, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement amongſt us, whereby trade will bee advanced; And ſo in a ſhort time, may a firm and laſting peace and ſafetie bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, the gain whereof will not onely equipoiz, but out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance all the charge that can bee ſpent, for obteining of the ſame. The blood that may bee ſpilt therein is in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing of the Lord Armipotent, the God of Battel, from whom our ſmall handfuls of men have not onely met with glorious, and moſt ſtrange, and often deliverances, far tranſcending the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99021:34"/>thoughts of natural man, in all their former ingagements, but maie (doubtleſs) exſpect it ſtill; and for thoſe that fall in the Lord's ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, they die not, but to live eternally in and with him, the true knowledg of whom teacheth us, that all our daies are numbred, and that not one life ſhall bee loſt, but by his fore purpoſe and divine appointment, who will ſtill eſpecially in our greateſt weakneſs, cover us with his ſhield in the daie of battel, and enable us to trample on the necks of his, and our enemies, and which is far more excellent, they ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee members of the Church, and live amongſt the Saints tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, whoſe death ſhall happen in a cauſ ſo juſt (God's cauſ.) And here it may bee noted that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels by their laſt immane cruelties, filling up the meaſure of their iniquitie ſeem to bee a people adopted by providence, to an utter exſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. Whereunto all faithful Engliſh-men have a call from Heaven, in vindication of that innocent bloud, there moſt profuſely ſpilt, without leaving that deteſtable brand of Aſtorgiſm upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation to perpetuitie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The Fifteenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVHether it bee not the dutie of the State, and Trustees of the Nation, rather to minde, ſeek and preſerv the general peace, ſafetie, and welfare of the whole Nation, then the honors and profits of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men; And whether particulnr men may not in an humble and peaceable manner preſent their thoughts to the State for a general good?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The fifteenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe whole <hi>Quere</hi> is affirmatively confeſſed, and therefore it is hoped, that <hi>Ireland</hi> (a Countrie appropriate to this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99021:34"/>Nation, and the major part of Inhabitants there of <hi>Engliſh</hi> deſcent will bee looked on, not as the honors and profits of particular men, but as a general concernment; the deſertion whereof will redound to the honors and profits of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men, enemies to the peace and welfare of <hi>England,</hi> the moſt malignant of its enemies, the Papiſts; and therefore particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, peaceable, wel-affected men ought in an humble and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manner, to preſent their thoughts thereof to the State for a general good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The ſixteenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>WHether if the State of <hi>England</hi> ſhould now in their full ſtrength proclaim <hi>Ireland</hi> a free State, repenting of all the evils that themſelvs have acted and intended, and that our King hath formerly acted againſt that Nation; and that they will not further act to their prejudice, but onely ſit down by them as a neighbor-State, as <hi>Holland</hi> doth, and that they onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that they may bee in mutual league, and as friends to ſeek the peace and welfare of each other, that they will not countenance, aſsiſt, or protect each other's enemies, nor anie that ſhall diſturb the peace, or ſafetie of anie of the Nation, and onely require ſom conſiderable Sea-Port-Towns as ſecuritie, and bond to tie the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to the performance of the Covenants; I ſaie, whether this may not bee everie waie as advantagious to the State, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> as a conqueſt over them, the charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99021:35"/>
                  <head>The ſixteenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>IF the State of <hi>England</hi> ſhould now in their full ſtrength pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim <hi>Ireland</hi> a free State, and do further, as in the <hi>Quere</hi> is propounded: yet our true knowledg and experience of the Rebel's diſpoſition promoniſheth that they will bee ſtill (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon anie occaſion of advantage) forward and readie to the uttermoſt of their powers, and malice, to cut their benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's throats, beſides it would bee the moſt prejudicial act that could bee imagined againſt the State, and people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> For <hi>ſet aſide</hi> the honor due to almightie God, in giving up that Countrie from his true worſhip and ſervice, to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and prophaneneſs; <hi>ſet aſide</hi> their guilt of the innocent blood of our brethren, kindred, and Nation there, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly poured out, which will doubtleſs hang over the heads of the Pardoners; <hi>ſet aſide</hi> the utter overthrow, and loſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thouſands of Families, their goods, and Eſtates, and the giving up the poor (yet conſiderable) remain of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant partie there, to the diſpoſition of their moſt cruel enemies; <hi>Set aſide</hi> the bloud and treaſure there ſpent out of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the rebellion, wherein not a Family in <hi>England</hi> but is intereſſed, and which they exſpect not to bee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered fruitleſs, to the diſhonor of the whole Nation; <hi>Set</hi> all theſe <hi>aſide:</hi> yet humane reaſon and policie dictate's, that the Houſ cannot bee ſafe ſo long as the back door is open. The father wrong's his poſteritie, if hee laviſhly give away halfe his inheritance, the regaining whereof, hereafter may bee a cauſe of ten fold loſs of blood and treaſure, to what it may coſt in preſervation; that it is neither ſafe or juſt in the Law of Nature, to fling away anie part of our Arms, or defence, though at preſent cumberſom, which may advantage the enemie by taking poſſeſſion of, and uſing (as the popiſh partie will) againſt us: And ſaie the right and intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> were not ſo great, cleer, and undeniable as it is: yet the late revolutions conſidered, <hi>England</hi> muſt never exſpect to bee advantaged, or anie waie bettered by deſerting <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99021:35"/>giving it up to the Rebellious Inhabitants; A people ſo foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and lately treacherous to the Proteſtants, and later <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Which people are neither ſo formidable in their beſt arms, defences, and power to keep themſelvs in ſuch a proclaimed condition or freedom; Nor is it the aim, or mark of their new Grandees to effect and maintein it, whoſe diviſions and contrarie inclinations amongſt themſelvs, are, and will ever bee a readie and open gap for anie <hi>England's</hi> enemies to enter in at: And ſaie they have no realitie in them to a kingly claim, (as without doubt they have not, they having now of late made amongſt them ſo manie new Kings) yet it were an Act of deſtructive and dangerous conſequence, to give <hi>Ireland</hi> to the diſpoſal of the Pope, and hee to the Spaniard (his dear childe) which the Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland</hi> are not much againſt, but contrariwiſe, manie of them deſire it, and which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly (if not prevented) would happen: And ſo that bit bee brought into the mouth of the Spaniard, which hee hath ſo long gaped after to ſwallow and devour.</p>
                  <p>And admit that <hi>Ireland</hi> were of the Proteſtant Religion, as well as <hi>England,</hi> and thereby the above inconveniencies avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: yet were it neither ſafe nor commendable, to quit the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of that Iſland on <hi>England,</hi> by proclaiming the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof a free State; ſince what ſuch a State might do upon verie ſlender grounds and miſtakes, let <hi>Scotland</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>The reſolution therefore is; that to do as this <hi>Quere</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound's, is extreme loſs, hazard, and diſadvantage to the people of <hi>England,</hi> and the reducement of that Countrie to its lawful dependance and Government of <hi>England,</hi> by a full conqueſt of the preſent Rebels (let the charge bee what it will) is more honorable, ſafe, profitable and advantagious to <hi>England,</hi> then to proclaim them a free State, who are not in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to make and keep themſelvs ſo, nor are or ever were a diſtinct Nation, as is before ſaid, and here take notice, how the <hi>Queriſt</hi> propound's a ſuitable reward indeed for the State of <hi>England,</hi> to beſtow upon the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their kindred and allies, acknowledging the ſaid Rebels a free State, and in amitie with them, and thereby for ever to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99021:36"/>quit their own undoubted intereſt, eſtabliſh the worſt of their enemies, becom guiltie of the unparalel'd murthers of thoſe, that were fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bone, and leav the remnant of the poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, continually open to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of thoſe whoſe mercies are cruelties. So as the <hi>Queriſt</hi> would work the State of <hi>England</hi> into an impious unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and unnatural deſertion of the cauſ of God, their own intereſt and National quarrel.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="question_and_answer">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>The ſeventeenth Quere.</head>
                  <p>VVhether <hi>Ireland</hi> were not altogether as like to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of protection ſafetie, and defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e from the State and people of <hi>England,</hi> as from <hi>Spain</hi> or any other Nation, eſpecially would they not rather then from Prince <hi>Charles, Rupert</hi> or from ſuch like forlorn Soldiers, how would they then ſtyle the malignant Partie inconſiderable, And whether they were not then likelie ſuddenly to recall their Sea-Pirats, and ſo ſuddenly ſet open all Trade by Sea?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The ſeventeenth Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>BEcauſ the Rebellious Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland</hi> have caſt off their obedience to the government of <hi>England,</hi> and (as is too well known) have plotted, and, as farr as they could, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored the utter ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tirpation of the Engliſh Proteſtants, have in coolneſs of bloud (and without any provocation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99021:36"/>them) maliciouſly and moſt barbarouſly murthered, ſom hundreds of thouſands of them, driven the reſt from their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, robbed them of their Eſtates, wounded, maimed, and moſt miſerably intreated great numbers of others, have burned their houſes, Caſiles and Churches, and have elected and made to and amongſt themſelvs ſeveral new Kings, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pope, the King of <hi>Spaine, Owen M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Art O Neil, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phelim O Neil,</hi> The Lord <hi>Maguire</hi> (ſince deceaſed) <hi>O Conner Dun</hi> of <hi>Sligoh, Philip M<hi rend="sub">c</hi> Hugh M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Sane O Rely, Dermot M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Doolin Cavenagh,</hi> and one <hi>O Shergil;</hi> as doth and will fully appear in the examinations taken in that behalf, and becauſ alſo thoſe rebellious Iriſh have declined all Engliſh government, returned to their barbarous manners and cuſtoms, have ſet up a new government, have vowed (and many of them taken the Sacrament) to deſtroy not only all the men, women and children of the Engliſh Proteſtants, but alſo all irrational Creatures of the Engliſh breed, and becauſ alſo they have in a moſt high manner, &amp; as farr as they could, prophaned the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, books and daies of God's true worſhip, have brought to death as many Profeſſors of his truth, as they could poſſiblie ſurpriſe, and have dilated their power and ſtrength, in the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perpetrating of any crime deſtructive to the Engliſh Proteſtants; and which might render themſelvs uncapable of mercie, protection or ſafetie from the people of <hi>England,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none ought to be given them; nor ought the ſword (now juſtly and upon neceſſitie drawn out againſt them) be returned to the Scabbard, before that deſtruction they denounced, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to execute upon the Engliſh, be retaliated upon themſelvs, &amp; leaſt ſuch mercie be recompenced with a curſ as the holie Ghoſt by the Prophet, in a caſe ſuch ſemblance, pronounced <hi>Jer.</hi> 28.10. <hi>Curſed bee bee that doth the work of the Lord negligently, and curſed bee hee that keepeth back his Sword from bloud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I wonder from what the Queriſt mean's they ſhould be protected, ſaved or defended; if hee intend it to bee from that puniſhment, they have ſo juſtly merited, by their Rebellion and wickedneſs paſt, according to that protection, and thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions they lately had by Compact with <hi>Ormond,</hi> grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Commiſſion from the late King <hi>Charle;</hi> To that I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99021:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>That if the indulgent Engliſh ſhould grant it to them, no doubt they would accept, and make uſe of it, ſo long as they ſhould finde it to promote and be conſiſtent with their own ends, and ſurely they would to themſelvs take up no little glorie to meet with ſuch a color of juſtification, as they might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by transferr their odious guilt upon the Protectors, ſo much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levate the policie and wit of the old Serpent (their dread Lord and Maſter) above the Engliſh Proteſtant <hi>genius;</hi> and bee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo the further enabled to deſtroy the remaining Partie of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi> (too precious wee hope) to bee the price of their ſecuritie. But for further reſolution,</p>
                  <p>Theſe rebellious Inhabitants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are ſo contemptuous to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> laws, ſo oppoſite in profeſſion to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant, ſo hardned in their wickedneſs, envie and hatred againſt God's truth, and them, for the truth's ſake, and ſo wil ully bent to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, as, till ſuppreſſed, they will not omit, but contrariwiſe with greedineſs, draw into their confederacie, countenance and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance any, whether forreign Prince or other perſon, and never think themſelvs in good condition or ſafetie, until (if poſſible) they have ſounded the dreinings of the Engliſh veins, to their abyſs, through their deepeſt lakes of bloud, and have brought the undeſtroied part of the Engliſh to the loweſt ebb of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie, which they will endeavour to effect and haſten on, as well by Sea as Land, and have in moſt eſteem all malignant Parties, lending a hand, and enabling them to effect it. But the Lord prevent them.</p>
                  <p>Something may bee ſaid concerning <hi>Edmond Gawre,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the formerly recited and anſwered cavilling Queres to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Theodore Jennings,</hi> who delivered them over to the Lord Preſident of the Council of State, as that it is verie like lie he is an Iriſhman, and one whom (by credible information) doth or lately did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly &amp; cnnningly ſhelter among the ſoldierie, in or about <hi>Londor,</hi> and is a Jeſuitical Papiſt, for the verie Queres themſelvs ſmel of the breath of a Jeſuit, the truth whereof may do well, if found out by inquiſition after his preſent being, parentage and education, which is left to the diſcretion of thoſe eminent perſons in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, the Impoſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s then preſent drift being to retard and hinder (if poſſible) forces and ſuccors from our Partie in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at that time, when the Land was in greateſt danger to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent and taken from us.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99021:37"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
